Hello friends, welcome all of you
नमस्कार दोस्तों, आप सभी का स्वागत है द
Ranveer at the show. Let's start this
रणवीर शो में। चलिए शुरू करते हैं यह
Interesting journey. Ok. Crisper Biggins
दिलचस्प सफर। ओके। क्रिसपर बिगिंस
Curing Genetic Disorders. tell me sir
क्योरिंग जेनेटिक डिसऑर्डर। बताइए सर
What is Crisper? CRISPR is a genetic
क्रिसपर क्या है? क्रिसपर एक जेनेटिक
Editing is technology. If you have a child
एडिटिंग टेक्नोलॉजी है। अगर आपको बच्चा
Do you want him to grow up to be 6 feet tall?
चाहिए आप चाहते हो कि वो बड़ा होकर 6 फुट
Make it 6 inches. If she has brown eyes then you
6 इंच का बनाए। उसके ब्राउन आइज हो तो आप
You can enter that code in it. you can have any
उसमें वो कोड डाल सकते हो। यू कैन हैव एनी
Designer characteristics that you want.
डिजाइनर कैरेक्टरिस्टिक्स दैट यू वांट।
Do You Think Human Cloning Is Reality
डू यू थिंक ह्यूमन क्लोनिंग रियलिटी
will it be made? It can be made even today. Technology is
बनेगी? आज भी बन सकती है। टेक्नोलॉजी तो
It is available. I took Ranveer's DNA
अवेलेबल है। मैंने रणवीर का डीएनए ले
Took it. For example, I stole every single hair
लिया। फॉर एग्जांपल एक एक बाल मैंने चोरी
I did it. From that I got your DNA
कर लिया। उससे मैंने आपका डीएनए
Extracted it. So I am Ranveer's new
एक्सट्रैक्ट किया। तो मैं रणवीर के नए
I can make a clone. Wow!
क्लोन बना सकता हूं। वाह!
When we say that AI will cause loss of
जब हम ये कहते हैं कि एआई विल कॉज लॉस ऑफ़
Jobs and Substitution of Jobs. this is a
जॉब्स और सब्सीट्यूशन ऑफ़ जॉब्स। दिस इज अ
Very real. We are there now. Today's India
वैरी रियल। वी आर देयर नाउ। आज इंडिया की
The entire IT industry is about to collapse.
आईटी इंडस्ट्री पूरी खत्म होने वाली है।
There is a chip that we put inside our brain
एक चिप है जो हम अपने ब्रेन के अंदर
with the outside world
डालेंगे जो बाहर की दुनिया के साथ
will be connected and we will connect them with our thoughts
कनेक्टेड होगा और हम अपने थॉट से उनको
Will be able to control. what do you think
कंट्रोल कर पाएंगे। क्या आपको लगता है
Will this become an actual reality by 20-30?
20-30 तक ये एक्चुअल रियलिटी बन जाएगी?
AI companions pass during test for
एआई कंपैनियंस पास ड्यूरिंग टेस्ट फॉर
Emotional bonding. it will have emotions just
इमोशनल बॉन्डिंग। इट विल हैव इमोशंस जस्ट
Like humans. You ain't got no wife
लाइक ह्यूमंस। आपको कोई पत्नी नहीं मिली
For example. So you adopted a robot
फॉर एग्जांपल। तो आपने एक रोबोट पाल लिया
Then that robot will be able to emote just
देन दैट रोबोट विल बी एबल टू इमोट जस्ट
Like human. Wow. artificially if you
लाइक ह्यूमन। वाह। आर्टिफिशियली अगर आप
Will make your children super intelligent
अपने बच्चों को सुपर इंटेलिजेंट बनाएंगे
it's gonna cause a buffercation of the human
इट्स गोना कॉज अ बफरर्केशन ऑफ़ द ह्यूमन
Rest in Super Intelligent Super Rich People
रेस्ट इनू सुपर इंटेलिजेंट सुपर रिच पीपल
And poor people who are left behind.
एंड पुअर पीपल हु आर लेफ्ट बिहाइंड।
This is the one with Abhijeet Chawla and Ranveer
यह अभिजीत चावड़ा और रणवीर वाली
The combination is legendary. But this
कॉम्बिनेशन तो लेजेंडरी है ही। पर इस
What I will say about this episode is that this
एपिसोड के बारे में मैं यह कहूंगा कि दिस
Is one of the most mind blowing episodes.
इज़ वन ऑफ़ द मोस्ट माइंड ब्लोइंग एपिसोड्स।
We enjoyed a lot. uh let's record this
बहुत एंजॉय करा हमने। अह इसे रिकॉर्ड करते
Time. I am sure you will enjoy it while
वक्त। आई एम श्योर यू विल एंजॉय इट व्हाइल
You listen. If you are also in future regime
यू लिसन। अगर आप भी फ्यूचर रिज्म में
Do you have interest? If you want to know that
इंटरेस्ट रखते हो। अगर आपको जानना है कि
What will happen because of AI? what after that
एआई की वजह से क्या होगा? उसके बाद क्या
will be?
होगा?
How will our life be? if you
में जिंदगी कैसी होगी हमारी? अगर आपको
If you like shows like Black Mirror then you
ब्लैक मिरर जैसे शोज़ अच्छे लगते हैं तो यू
will enjoy this future special v abhijeet
विल एंजॉय दिस फ्यूचर स्पेशल वि अभिजीत
Chavda on DRS.
चावड़ा ऑन डी आर एस।
[music]
[संगीत]
We have been planning this podcast for several years.
इस पॉडकास्ट को हमने काफी सालों से प्लान
I have done it. but today we are executing
करके रखा है। पर आज वी आर एग्जीक्यूटिंग
Upon it. Futurism. it's called futurism
अपॉन इट। फ्यूचरिज्म। फ्यूचरिज्म ही कहते
Are. Let's talk about futurism. Yes.
हैं। फ्यूचरिज्म बोलते हैं। यस।
Today we will talk about futurism.
फ्यूचरिज्म के बारे में बात करेंगे आज।
That means it is a bit tech oriented
यानी कि ये थोड़ा सा ये टेक ओरिएंटेड
It is a podcast but there will be an element of cleaning,
पडकास्ट है बट सफाई का एलिमेंट रहेगा,
The element of science will remain and that of the future
साइंस का एलिमेंट रहेगा और फ्यूचर का
The element will remain. The way AI has changed the world
एलिमेंट रहेगा। जिस तरह एआई ने दुनिया को
changed it in the same way many new ones
बदल दिया उसी तरह ऐसे बहुत सारे नए
Technologies are coming that will transform the world into every
टेक्नोलॉजीस आने वाले हैं जो दुनिया को हर
Will change in 5 year chapter. We are Sir today
5 साल के चैप्टर में बदलेंगे। हम सर आज के
What do you think about the podcast episode?
पडकास्ट एपिसोड के बारे में आप क्या
Would you like to give a preview to the audience? See
प्रीव्यू देना चाहेंगे ऑडियंस को? देखिए
We will see in five years' time.
हम पांचप साल के इंटरवल में देखेंगे
What new technologies may come? We
क्या-क्या नई टेक्नोलॉजीस आ सकती है। हमने
AI has been asked what it thinks
एआई को पूछा है कि उनके हिसाब से क्या
The next five years are going to be next
होने वाला है नेक्स्ट फाइव इयर्स नेक्स्ट
five years in the next five years and every
फाइव इयर्स नेक्स्ट फाइव इयर्स में और हर
How much will we review the prediction
प्रेडिक्शन को हम रिव्यु करेंगे कितना
Is it accurate and how timely is it? is this
एक्यूरेट है कितना टाइमली है? क्या ये
It could be sooner than that or it could take some more time
जल्दी हो सकता है उससे या फिर और टाइम
It will be repeated and so on. gave a tremendous output
लगेगा एंड सो ऑन। एक जबरदस्त आउटपुट दिया
we have chat gpt and parallelly i have
है हमें चैट जीपीटी ने एंड पैरेलली आई हैव
Also got chat gpt in my hand. Ahhh
आल्सो गॉट चैट जीपीटी इन माय हैंड। अह
Wherever we both get stuck,
जहां भी हम दोनों अटक जाएंगे विद
Respect to Some Technology We Will
रिस्पेक्ट टू सम टेक्नोलॉजी वी विल
Reference Chat GPT. Good idea. that ah
रेफरेंस चैट जीपीटी। गुड आईडिया। कि अह
Advancement in the subject of flying cars
फ्लाइंग कार्स के सब्जेक्ट में एडवांसमेंट
What is? Advancements in Nano-bots
क्या है? नैनो बॉट्स में एडवांसमेंट
What is it? And so on. so we will use
क्या-क्या है? वगैरह-वगैरह। सो वी विल यूज़
The Help of AI. So this is TRS's first
द हेल्प ऑफ़ एआई। इसलिए ये टीआरएस का पहला
Episodes where there is Actively One and a Half Guest
एपिसोड है जहां एक्टिवली वन एंड हाफ गेस्ट
I am sitting. one guest in front of me which
बैठे हुए हैं। वन गेस्ट इन फ्रंट मी व्हिच
Is ac. And I have half a guess on my phone. in
इज़ एसी। और एक आधा गेस मेरे फोन पर है। इन
The Form of Chat GBT. Ok. ahh, you want to
द फॉर्म ऑफ़ चैट GBटी। ओके। अह, यू वांट टू
Talk about the prompt we gave? We
टॉक अबाउट द प्रम्प्ट टू वी गेव? हमने
What was the prompt given to Ah Chat GBT?
प्रोम्पट क्या दिया था अह चैट जीबीटी को?
ah please predict the technologies
अह प्लीज प्रेड प्रिडिक्ट दी टेक्नोलॉजीस
that could emerge in the future in the eight five
दैट कुड इमर्ज इन द फ्यूचर इन द एट फाइव
Year intervals till under 2,000, right?
ईयर इंटरवल्स अंटिल अंडर 2,000, राइट?
2,200, 200. Yes. Which is very far away. but came
2,200, 200। यस। जो बहुत दूर है। पर आई
think it's important to know these concepts
थिंक इट्सेंट टू नो दीज़ कांसेप्ट्स
because I promise you if your business
क्योंकि अ आई प्रॉमिस यू अगर आपके बिज़नेस
ambitions in life or if you just
एंबिशंस हैं जिंदगी में या अगर आप बस
If you want mental stimulation, you will gain a
मेंटल स्टिमुलेशन चाहते हो, यू विल गेन अ
Lot from this episode. Ok? so lets
लॉट फ्रॉम दिस एपिसोड। ओके? सो लेट्स
begin sir at 2025 which is now which is
बिगिन सर एट 2025 व्हिच इज नाउ व्हिच इज
Now AI can be used as pilot in vehicles
नाउ एआई को पायलट्स इन व्हीकल्स
Revolutionised Transport and Crisper
रेवोल्यूशननाइज्ड ट्रांसपोर्ट एंड क्रिसपर
Begins curing genetic disorders
बिगिंस क्योरिंग जेनेटिक डिसऑर्डर्स
AI Copilots in Vehicles Revolution
एआई कोपायलट्स इन व्हीकल्स रेवोल्यूशन
Transport I Think I'm Talking About Tesla
ट्रांसपोर्ट आई थिंक टॉकिंग अबाउट टेस्ला
style tesla style auto driving a
स्टाइल टेस्ला स्टाइल ऑटो ड्राइविंग अ
cars are still in countries like the US where
कार्स तो अभी यूएस जैसे कंट्रीज में जहां
But there are very good traffic rules
पर बहुत अच्छे-अच्छे ट्रैफिक रूल्स हैं
We already have self driving there
वहां पे वी ऑलरेडी हैव सेल्फ ड्राइविंग
Cars have software inside them, earn it!
कार्स उसके अंदर सॉफ्टवेयर है अर्न इट हैज़
access to the and to the visual aids so that
एक्सेस टू दी और टू दी विजुअल एड्स तो वह
The car can drive itself. we are
कार अपने आप को ड्राइव कर सकती है। हम तो
I don't think it is legal to drive here
आई डोंट थिंक इट इज़ लीगल हियर टू ड्राइव
it like that but that technology has arrived
इट लाइक दैट लेकिन वो टेक्नोलॉजी आ चुकी
Is. so i think it's gonna be implemented
है। सो आई थिंक इट्स गोना बी इंप्लीमेंटेड
Now so AI copilot so you sit you AI
नाउ सो एआई कोपायलट तो आप बैठिए आप एआई को
Brother, tell me if I want to go to this place
बोलिए कि भाई आप मुझे ये जगह जाना है तो
He will take you along so we are almost there
आपको लेके जाएगा वो सो वी आर ऑलमोस्ट देयर
Right Now or So That It Makes Sense to AI
राइट नाउ या सो दैट इट मेक्स सेंस एआई को
Pilot do you think it will be possible in India.
पायलट डू यू थिंक भारत में पॉसिबल होगा।
It is a bit challenging in India because India
भारत में थोड़ा चैलेंजिंग है क्योंकि भारत
There are no traffic rules. No one in India
में ट्रैफिक रूल्स नहीं है। भारत में कोई
He keeps doing anything. So AI will have to
कुछ भी करता रहता है। सो एआई विल हैव टू
Do Vai Defensive Driving. if in india
डू वै डिफेंसिव ड्राइविंग। अगर भारत में
if it has to be implemented then and for this reason
उसको इम्लीमेंट करना है तो और इस कारण
Because of road conditions are also a problem
बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ रोड कंडीशंस भी एक प्रॉब्लम होता
Is. So it is a bit challenging in India
है। सो भारत में थोड़ा चैलेंजिंग है इसको
Implement it at least at this time. Edge
इंप्लीमेंट करना इस समय पे एटलीस्ट। एज
Far as I know. When you're now in a Tesla
फार एज आई नो। जब आप अब एक Tesla में
When you sit, there is a screen in the middle.
बैठते हो तो एक स्क्रीन होती है बीच में।
Software updates for more Tesla cars
और Tes्ला कार्स के सॉफ्टवेयर अपडेट्स
It keeps happening. One of the recent updates
होते जाते हैं। वन ऑफ द रीसेंट अपडेट्स
Aloud mapping of the near surroundings. i.e
अलाउड मैपिंग ऑफ द नियर सराउंडिंग्स। यानी
that when you're actually driving a Tesla
कि जब आप एक्चुअली Tes्ला चला रहे हो तो
If a truck is going in front of you, your
अगर आपके सामने एक ट्रक जा रही है अ योर
Tesla is able to understand that truck is
Tesla इज़ एबल टू अंडरस्टैंड कि ट्रक है
in front and that's not on the screen but a truck
सामने और वो स्क्रीन पर ना एक ट्रक की
The image appears. it can also
इमेज दिखाई देती है। इट कैन आल्सो
Identify people. it can also identify
आइडेंटिफाई पीपल। इट कैन आल्सो आइडेंटिफाई
Those who live in western countries
वो जो वेस्टर्न कंट्रीज में कोस रहते हैं
na chote road pe which doesn't allow you to go
ना छोटे रोड पे व्हिच डोंट अलाउ यू टू गो
On that. So technology has reached your place
ऑन दैट। सो टेक्नोलॉजी हैज़ रीच्ड योर जहां
You get that 3D imagery in real time
रियल टाइम में आपको एक वो 3D इमेजरी मिल
It goes around you. I am sure it is
जाती है आपके आसपास। आई एम श्योर इट्स
Using the Same Imagery to Facilitate the Self
यूजिंग द सेम इमेजरी टू फैसिलिटेट द सेल्फ
Driving. Absolutely yes. so it's like
ड्राइविंग। बिल्कुल यस। तो इट्स इट्स लाइक
A LiDAR like system of the radar mapping type
अ लीडर लाइक सिस्टम रेडार मैपिंग टाइप का
He knows what is in front of him. So
उसको मालूम पड़ता है सामने क्या है। तो
According to that he creates the whole imagery
उसके हिसाब से वो वो पूरा इमेजरी बनाता
Is. And that is what you use it for
है। एंड दैट इज व्हाट यूज इट यूज टू
Navigate. same i don't know how it would do it
नेविगेट। वही आई डोंट नो हाउ इट वुड डू इट
On Indian Roads. because because indian
ऑन इंडियन रोड्स। बिकॉज़ बिकॉज़ इंडियन
The conditions are evolving very fast and you
कंडीशंस बहुत ही फास्ट इवॉल्विंग है और आप
Predictive
प्रेडिक्टिव
Can't analyze what's next
एनालिसिस नहीं कर सकते कि नेक्स्ट क्या
It is going to happen. Suddenly someone ahead on the road
होने वाला है। रास्ते में कोई आगे अचानक
From Against the Rules. so i think india
से अगेंस्ट द रूल्स। तो आई थिंक इंडिया
It will happen eventually in me too. May B and
में भी इवेंचुअली तो होगा ही। मे बी और
It will take three, four, maybe five years. But
तीन चार मेबी शायद पांच साल लगेंगे। लेकिन
Eventually the technology will grow to such an extent that
इवेंचुअली टेक्नोलॉजी उतना बढ़ जाएगा कि
It can run autonomously in India too
भारत में भी वो चला सके ऑटोनॉमसली
To the vehicles. We
व्हीकल्स को। हम
Suppose this is the situation of an autonomous vehicle
मान लो यह ऑटोनॉमस व्हीकल की सिचुएशन
actually
एक्चुअली
It became real. Yes.
रियल बन गई। हां।
that's a very simple way of a lot of people
दैट्स अ वेरी सिंपल वे ऑफ़ अ लॉट ऑफ़ पीपल
Losing their jobs. A lot of people who are on Uber
लूजिंग देयर जॉब्स। बहुत सारे जो Uber
there are drivers who are taxi drivers,
ड्राइवर्स हैं, जो टैक्सी ड्राइवर्स हैं,
those who are rickshaw drivers, they will have to
जो रिक्शा ड्राइवर्स हैं, दे विल हैव टू
Look for other occupations. Yes. So when we
लुक फॉर अदर ऑक्युपेशन्स। यस। तो जब हम ये
Says AI will cause loss of jobs and
कहते हैं कि एआई विल कॉज लॉस ऑफ़ जॉब्स और
Substitution of Jobs. this is a very
सब्सीट्यूशन ऑफ़ जॉब्स। दिस इज अ वेरी
Real. We are there now. We are already there.
रियल। वी आर देयर नाउ। वी आर ऑलरेडी देयर।
In 10-15 years. No, today India has five
10-15 साल में। नहीं पांच आज इंडिया की
The entire IT industry is about to collapse.
आईटी इंडस्ट्री पूरी खत्म होने वाली है।
Let us tell you, there are AI agents. AI
हम बताओ देखिए एआई एजेंट्स होते हैं। एआई
Agent means it's an AI system that
एजेंट मतलब इट्स अ एक एआई सिस्टम है जिसके
He has all these competencies. From the lates I've
पास ये सारे कंपटेंसेस है। लेट्स से मैंने
Requirements for an AI Agent
एआई एजेंट को एक रिक्वायरमेंट्स
gave the document and a dis document
डॉक्यूमेंट दिया और एक डिज़ डॉक्यूमेंट
of the given software. He will read it and his
दिया सॉफ्टवेयर का। वो उसको पढ़ेगा और उसके
Use whatever skill sets he has
उसके पास जो भी स्किल सेट्स है उसको यूज़
He will make the software and give it to you. He
करके वो सॉफ्टवेयर बना के देगा आपको। वह
An AI agent who is a programmer. Now
एक एआई एजेंट जो है प्रोग्रामर है। अब
We will give its output to another AI agent.
उसका आउटपुट हम देंगे दूसरे एआई एजेंट को
Who is the tester? He will do the unit testing.
जो टेस्टर है। वह यूनिट टेस्टिंग कर लेगा,
will do regression testing and whatever else
रिग्रेशन टेस्टिंग कर लेगा और जो कुछ भी
He got the bugs back from the programming agent
उसको बग्स मिले वापस प्रोग्रामिंग एजेंट
Will give it to. Programming agents, all that.
को देगा। प्रोग्रामिंग एजेंट्स वो सब
It will appear and solve the bugs. Back
दिखेगा और बग्स को सॉल्व कर देगा। वापस
Testing will be done. once everything is
टेस्टिंग हो जाएगा। वंस एवरीथिंग इज़
Approved. You give it to the client. Where
अप्रूव्ड। आप क्लाइंट को दीजिए खत्म। कहां
But is your human programmer in this? Where
पे है आपका ह्यूमन प्रोग्रामर इसमें? कहां
But do you have a human tester in this? India
पे आपका ह्यूमन टेस्टर है इसमें? इंडिया
The entire IT industry could be destroyed by this
का पूरा आईटी इंडस्ट्री इससे खत्म हो सकता
Is. So we are almost already there today.
है। सो वी आर ऑलमोस्ट ऑलरेडी देयर टुडे।
All the entrepreneurs we have nowadays are like me
हम जितने भी एंटरप्रेन्यर्स आजकल मुझसे
Let's all talk about AI agents
मिलते हैं हम हर कोई एआई एजेंट्स के बारे
I am talking to you. g a agent word meaning
में जी बात करता है। जी अ एजेंट शब्द मतलब
What? AI Agent is the simplest definition of this
क्या? एआई एजेंट सबसे सिंपल डेफिनेशन इसका
That's it, he's one of your AI employees. Yours
ये है कि वो आपका एक एआई एंप्लई है। आपका
You hired a programmer. For
आपने एक एक प्रोग्रामर हायर किया। फॉर
A skill set that an example programmer has
एग्जांपल प्रोग्रामर के पास एक स्किल सेट
Is. He knows these programming languages
है। ये ये प्रोग्रामिंग लैंग्वेज उसको आते
Are. Take the design document to him
हैं। उसको डिज़ाइन डॉक्यूमेंट लेकर अ
I know how to code. Doing Unit Testing
कोडिंग करना आता है। यूनिट टेस्टिंग करना
It comes. he can communicate with testing
आता है। ही कैन कम्युनिकेट विद टेस्टिंग
Employees and so on. AI Agent One
एंप्लाइजज़ एंड सो ऑन। एआई एजेंट एक
The software is your employee. AI Enabled
सॉफ्टवेयर एंप्लई है आपका। एआई इनेबल्ड
Employee That's the Simplest Definition
एम्प्लई दैट्स दैट्स द सिंपलेस्ट डेफिनेशन
of the AI ​​agent. Ok. a little
एआई एजेंट का। ओके। एक छोटी सी
Experiment. Yes absolutely. Ok. Hey
एक्सपेरिमेंट करें। जी बिल्कुल। ओके। हे
chat gpt can you tell me when
चैट जीपीटी कैन यू टेल मी व्हेन
There won't be a requirement for any Uber
देयर वोंट बी अ रिक्वायरमेंट फॉर एनी उबर
Taxi drivers because self driving
टैक्सी ड्राइवर्स बिकॉज़ सेल्फ ड्राइविंग
Wood may have become an automated job in the future
वुड हैव बिकम एन ऑटोमेटेड जॉब इन द फ्यूचर
As These Cars in the Future Will Be Driven
एज़ इन कार्स इन द फ्यूचर विल बी ड्रिवन
Bye AI bots. There for Uber drivers
बाय AI बॉट्स। देयर फॉर Uber ड्राइवर्स
I don't have a job to do. Realistically
वोंट हैव अ जॉब टू डू। रियलिस्टिकली
according to you when you predict that
अकॉर्डिंग टू यू व्हेन यू प्रिडिक्ट दैट
That is a reality. Self-driving tech
दैट इज़ अ रियलिटी। सेल्फ ड्राइविंग टेक
already exists and is operational in
ऑलरेडी एक्सिस्ट एंड इज़ ऑपरेशनल इन
LIMITED CONDITIONS. Google is a company
लिमिटेड कंडीशंस। Google की एक कंपनी है
VMO Fully Driverless Robotaxi Services
VMO फुल्ली ड्राइवरलेस रोबोटक्सी सर्विज
in Phoenix Arizona and San Francisco
इन फिनिक्स एरिजोना एंड सैन फ्रांसिस्को
Cruise by General Motors doing same till
क्रूज बाय जनरल मोटर्स डूइंग सेम अंटिल
Regulatory issues paused it Tesla made a full
रेगुलेटरी इशूज़ पॉज्ड इट Tes्ला ने एक फुल
Self-driving service has been tested.
सेल्फ ड्राइविंग सर्विस को टेस्ट किया है।
It's in beta but requires humans
इट्स इन बीटा बट रिक्वायर्स ह्यूमन
Supervision Realistic Global Timeline
सुपरविज़न रियलिस्टिक ग्लोबल टाइमलाइन
Breakdown
ब्रेकडाउन
2027 to 2029 Dubai San Francisco
2027 टू 2029 दुबई सैन फ्रांसिस्को
Fully autonomous Uber like in Singapore
सिंगापुर में फुल्ली ऑटोनॉमस Uber लाइक
Flats in certain areas by 2030 to 35
फ्लट्स इन सर्टेन एरियाज बाय 2030 टू 35
Wherever there are developed cities there will be autonomous
जहां भी डिवेप शहर होंगे वहां ऑटोनॉमस
Driving will happen Driver job loss begins at
ड्राइविंग होगी ड्राइवर जॉब लॉस बिगिंस एट
Scale in Places Like California UAE
स्केल इन प्लेसेस लाइक कैलिफोर्निया यूएई
and parts of china by 204 40 majority
एंड पार्ट्स ऑफ चाइना बाय 204 40 मेजॉरिटी
of Uber rides in first world urban
ऑफ़ उबर राइड्स इन फर्स्ट वर्ल्ड अर्बन
Areas will be autonomous.
एरियाज विल बी ऑटोनॉमस।
Developing countries like India, Brazil,
डेवलपिंग कंट्रीज लाइक इंडिया, ब्राजील,
Africa Will Still Rely on Humans
अफ्रीका विल स्टिल रिलाई ऑन ह्यूमन
Drivers because of bad infrastructure,
ड्राइवर्स बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ बैड इंफ्रास्ट्रक्चर,
Legal Issues and Affordability
लीगल इश्यूज एंड अफोर्डेबिलिटी
But by 20-50 most global urban rights
बट बाय 20-50 मोस्ट ग्लोबल अर्बन राइट्स
Will be autonomous. Hmm. Manual Driving
विल बी ऑटोनॉमस। हम्म। मैनुअल ड्राइविंग
Becomes a niche and luxury experience.
बिकम्स अ नीश और लग्जरी एक्सपीरियंस।
Uber driver as a job could vanish in urban areas
Uber ड्राइवर एज़ अ जॉब कुड वैनिश इन अर्बन
Zons. That is to say, 25 years
ज़ों्स। यानी कि यह कह रहे हैं कि 25 साल
I will lose jobs. Look at India like
में जॉब्स चले जाएंगे। देखिए भारत जैसे
what happens in the country that we have taxi
देश में क्या होता है कि वी हैव टैक्सी
Driver unions who are in politics
ड्राइवर यूनियंस हु आर इन पॉलिटिकल उसमें
Politics also comes into play. so because of
पॉलिटिक्स भी आता है। सो बिकॉज़ ऑफ़
politics in because of these unions you may
पॉलिटिक्स इन बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ दीज़ यूनियंस यू मे
Have delays in these things. but i think by
हैव डिलेज़ इन दीज़ थिंग्स। बट आई थिंक बाय
20-40 in any reasonable country you will have
20-40 इन एनी रीज़नेबल कंट्री यू विल हैव
Autonomous drivers. Perhaps this is a developed
ऑटोनॉमस ड्राइवर्स। शायद ये एक डेवलप्ड
There will also be a country sign. Yes absolutely. Yes.
कंट्री की साइन भी होगी। हां बिल्कुल। यस।
Like if autonomous driving in your country
लाइक अगर आपके देश में ऑटोनॉमस ड्राइविंग
Bye 20-40 is not happening. it means you are
नहीं हो रही है बाय 20-40। इट मीन्स यू आर
A Backward Country Essentially. Ok. Ok.
अ बैकवर्ड कंट्री एसेंशियली। ओके। ओके।
now moving on because i am sure we will
नाउ मूविंग ऑन बिकॉज़ आई एम श्योर वी विल
Talk about the future of transport in the
टॉक अबाउट फ्यूचर ऑफ़ ट्रांसपोर्ट इन द
The future of this podcast also. Ok. Who
फ्यूचर ऑफ़ दिस पॉडकास्ट आल्सो। ओके। जो
The second prediction is for 2025 CRISPR
दूसरी प्रेडिक्शन है फॉर 2025 क्रिसपर
Begins curing genetic disorders.
बिगिंस क्योरिंग जेनेटिक डिसऑर्डर्स।
Tell me Sir what is Crisper? Crisper One
बताइए सर क्रिसपर क्या है? क्रिसपर एक
Genetic editing technology. What are jeans
जेनेटिक एडिटिंग टेक्नोलॉजी है। जींस क्या
it occurs? What are jeans? See our
होती है? जींस क्या होती है? देखिए हमारे
Accept for red in every cell in the body
शरीर में हर सेल में एक्सेप्ट फॉर रेड
Blood cells contain DNA like other cells
ब्लड सेल्स में बाकी सेल्स में डीएनए होता
Is. DNA is a very complicated thing
है। डीएनए एक बहुत ही कॉम्प्लिकेटेड बहुत
It is a big molecule. Ok? in that DNA
बड़ा मॉलिक्यूल है। ठीक है? उस डीएनए में
within our own structure
जो अपना जो स्ट्रक्चर है उसके अंदर हमारा
The genetic code is encoded. that when a child
जेनेटिक कोड एनकोडेड है। कि कोई बच्चा जब
what about his eyes when he is born
पैदा होता है तब उसके उसके आंख का क्या
will it be colour? What colour will his hair be?
कलर होगा? उसके बाल का क्या कलर होगा?
How light or dark will her skin be?
उसका स्किन कितना लाइट होगा, कितना डार्क
will be? How intelligent will he be that big
होगा? कितना इंटेलिजेंट होगा वो कि बड़ा
How tall and short will it become
होकर कितना टॉल कितना शॉर्ट बनेगा ये सारे
The Characteristics Inside Your DNA
कैरेक्टरिस्टिक्स आपके डीएनए के अंदर
is encoded and in your genetic code
एनकोडेड है और आपके जेनेटिक कोड में
Sometimes there may be some defects also
कभी-कभी कुछ डिफेक्ट्स भी हो सकते हैं
Due to which you may get genetic diseases.
जिसके कारण से आपको जेनेटिक डिसीज हो सकते
Are. For example, in some people's hearts
हैं। फॉर एग्जांपल कुछ लोगों के हृदय में
There is a hole. some children have this
एक होल होता है। कुछ बच्चों में ये होता
if it is then it would cause blue baby syndrome
है तो उस उससे ब्लू बेबी सिंड्रोम होता
Is. His skin turns bluish and
है। उसकी उसका स्किन ब्लूइश हो जाता है और
For that surgery has to be done. some people
उसके लिए सर्जरी करना पड़ता है। कुछ लोगों
there is a cliff pet which is here
को क्लिफ्ट पैेट होता है जो यहां पे कुछ
Some cuts happen. what some people say
कुछ कट होता है। कुछ लोगों में क्या बोलते
Are? Down syndrome happens and so on.
हैं? डाउन सिंड्रोम होता है एंड सो ऑन।
There are some such genetic diseases. Spina
कुछ-कुछ ऐसे जेनेटिक डिसीज हैं। स्पाइना
bafida for example that also possibly is
बफीडा फॉर एग्जांपल दैट आल्सो पॉसिबली इज़
A genetic disease. so all these are rare
अ जेनेटिक डिजीज। तो ये सारे रेयर
There are defects in your genetics that you may have
डिफेक्ट्स हैं जो आपके जेनेटिक्स में आपको
You can inherit those things. So Crisper is a
यू कैन इनहेरिट दोज़ थिंग्स। तो क्रिसपर एक
Genetic editing is a technology that is used in five
जेनेटिक एडिटिंग टेक्नोलॉजी है जो पांच छ
years ago me too seven years ago me
साल पहले मैं भी सात साल पहले मुझे
I don't remember it exactly. it's a recent
एक्सैक्टली याद नहीं है। इट्स अ रीसेंट
that thing has developed to him and those who
थिंग उसको वो डेवलप हुई है और जिन्होंने
Nobel Prize was given to those who developed this technology
इस टेक्नोलॉजी को डेवलप किया उनको नोबेल
I also got a prize for that. right now this
प्राइज भी मिला उसके लिए। अभी इस
Through technology you can customize individual genes
टेक्नोलॉजी के थ्रू आप इंडिविजुअल जींस को
You can edit it. So if you want a baby
एडिट कर सकते हो। तो अगर आपको बच्चा चाहिए
Ok? The new baby is going to be yours. You
ओके? नया बच्चा आपका होने वाला है। आप
Do you want him to grow up to be a man?
चाहते हो कि वो बड़ा होकर अगर पुरुष है तो
If you are 6 foot 6 inch tall then you can wear that coat in it
6 फुट 6 इंच का बने तो आप उसमें वो कोट
You can put it. If you need that his
डाल सकते हो। अगर आपको चाहिए कि उसके
If you have brown eyes or green eyes then you
ब्राउन आइज हो या फिर ग्रीन आइज हो तो आप
They can do that too. if you have red hair
वो भी कर सकते हैं। अगर आपको लाल बाल
If that child needs it, you can do that too
चाहिए उस बच्चे के तो वो भी आप कर सकते
Are. So whatever characteristics you
हैं। तो आपको जो भी कैरेक्टरिस्टिक्स
Theoretically you can do all this.
चाहिए थ्योरेटिकली आप ये सब कर सकते हो।
But for that the technology is a little different
लेकिन उसके लिए वो टेक्नोलॉजी थोड़ी और
It has to be advance. So I think we are going to do that right now
एडवांस होनी पड़ेगी। तो आई थिंक हम अभी उस
we're getting to the level where
स्तर पर पहुंच रहे हैं जहां पर हम
Can do this editing reliably. So for this
रिलायबली ये एडिटिंग कर सके। तो इसके लिए
He is making this prediction and we are
वो ये प्रेडिक्शन कर रहा है एंड वी आर
Almost there now. Ok
ऑलमोस्ट देयर नाउ। ओके
Right now our
अभी हमारे
Let's bring five guests to this show. Let go
फाइव गेस्ट्स को इस शो में लाते हैं। चलिए
Hi GPT please talk in Hindi.
हाय जीपीटी प्लीज हिंदी में बात कीजिए।
The podcast is being recorded here. a hindi
पडकास्ट रिकॉर्ड हो रहा है यहां। अ हिंदी
Welcome all podcast listeners to me
में सारे पडकास्ट लिसनर्स का स्वागत कीजिए
On The Ranveer Show. Hello friends, all of you
द रणवीर शो में। नमस्कार दोस्तों, आप सभी
Welcome to The Ranveer Show. Today's our
का स्वागत है द रणवीर शो में। आज की हमारी
The conversation is going to be very special. So connect
बातचीत होने वाली है बेहद खास। तो जुड़े
Stay tuned and let's get this interesting started
रहिए और चलिए शुरू करते हैं यह दिलचस्प
Journey. Ok. Chavda sir also sat with us
सफर। ओके। चावड़ा सर भी हमारे साथ बैठे
This is Abhijeet Chavda. Say hi to them too.
हैं अभिजीत चावड़ा। उनको भी हाय बोलिए।
Hello Abhijeet Chavda Sir. I am very happy
नमस्कार अभिजीत चावड़ा सर। बहुत खुशी है
Seeing you on the show. for today's discussion
आपको शो पर देखकर। आज की चर्चा के लिए
Very excited. Ok. please human
बहुत उत्साहित है। ओके। प्लीज ह्यूमन
use am and are like beings so that
बीइंग की तरह अम्स और अर्स यूज कीजिए ताकि
It felt like there was a real person sitting next to us
ये लगे कि एक असली इंसान बैठा है हमारे
It is not that he has gone with me. Yes absolutely. So
साथ ना कि ये गया है। जी बिल्कुल। तो
Abhijeet sir i want you for today's conversation
अभिजीत सर आपसे मतलब आज की बातचीत के लिए
We are very excited and hope that
हम काफी एक्साइटेड हैं और उम्मीद है कि
Our listeners also liked this episode very much.
हमारे लिसनर्स को भी यह एपिसोड काफी पसंद
will come. The document you generated
आएगा। वो जो आपने डॉक्यूमेंट जनरेट करी थी
not on which we made all those predictions
ना जिस पे हमने वो सब प्रेडिक्शनंस किए
Were. A, we just placed that document in front of us.
थे। अ वो अभी डॉक्यूमेंट हमने सामने रखी।
Do you remember that document we saw this afternoon?
याद है वो डॉक्यूमेंट इस दोपहर को हमने
It was generated. Yes, I remember that document.
जनरेट करी थी। हां वो डॉक्यूमेंट याद है
You have mentioned future projections and plans in it.
आपने उसमें फ्यूचर प्रोजेक्शंस और प्लांस
Had written. What is special about it?
लिखे थे। उसमें कौन सी खास बात पर बात
Do you want to do it now? So the public should not get any
करनी है अभी? तो जनता को ना पांच
Tell us about Crisper in sentences.
सेंटेंसेस में बताइए क्रिसपर के बारे में।
how to give a baby crisper technology
एक बच्चे को आप क्रिसपर टेक्नोलॉजी कैसे
Will you explain? Tell that to the public. Listen to the audience
समझाओगे? वो बताइए जनता को। ऑडियंस सुन
I am paying attention to what you say. Absolutely. So
रही है आपकी बातें ध्यान से। बिल्कुल। तो
CRISPR is a biotechnological tool that helps us
क्रिसपर एक जैव तकनीकी औजार है जो हमें
Gives the power to make changes in DNA.
डीएनए में बदलाव करने की ताकत देता है।
Just like we edit text on a computer
जैसे कंप्यूटर में हम टेक्स्ट एडिट करते
Similarly, it changes our genes
हैं वैसे ही यह हमारी जीन में बदलाव कर
Can. It helps in curing diseases, growing crops
सकता है। इससे बीमारियां ठीक करने, फसलें
improve or create new life structures
बेहतर बनाने या नई जीव संरचनाएं बनाने में
It helps. In simple words it is a biological
मदद मिलती है। सरल शब्दों में यह एक जैविक
There is a cut, copy, and paste tool. Ok. not me now
कट, कॉपी, पेस्ट टूल है। ओके। अभी ना मुझे
tell me in the next 5 years
यह बताइए कि अगले 5 सालों में
Realistically
रियलिस्टिकली
Crisper's can change a person's life
एक इंसान की लाइफ बदल सकती है क्रिसपर के
Tell us through your mind
थ्रू वो बताइए हमें आपके दिमाग के
According to.
अकॉर्डिंग।
In the next 5 years, humans will be able to use CRISPR
अगले 5 सालों में क्रिसपर से इंसानों की
Some important changes may happen in your life
जिंदगी में कुछ महत्वपूर्ण बदलाव आ सकते
Are. Treatment of certain genetic diseases such as
हैं। जैसे कुछ जेनेटिक बीमारियों का इलाज
It may be possible. for whom there was no treatment before
संभव हो सकता है। जिनके लिए पहले कोई इलाज
It was not there. even in diseases like cancer
नहीं था। कैंसर जैसी बीमारियों में भी
Targeted therapies may be developed. it
टारगेटेड थेरेपीस विकसित हो सकती हैं। यह
How are you feeling? We have been podcasting for 5 years
कैसा लग रहा है आपको? हम 5 साल से पडकास्ट
I have been doing this for one year. but it happened before
कर रहे हैं एक साल। पर पहले हो गया
How to podcast?
पडकास्ट कैसे?
no no there is magic with such which
नहीं नहीं देयर इज़ मैजिक विद एसी व्हिच
Can't be replaced. A ok. but not one
कांट बी रिप्लेस्ड। अ ओके। बट एक ना
We generate the text. we are 20
टेक्स्ट जनरेट कर देते हैं हम। हम् 20
Years From Now
इयर्स फ्रॉम नाउ
what will crisper
व्हाट विल क्रिसपर
Be able to do as long as it generates
बी एबल टू डू जब तक यह जनरेट करता है
She responds, you tell me what that means
रिस्पांस करती है आप बताइए कि मतलब
How does CRISPR actually work?
क्रिसपर एक्चुअली काम कैसे करता है व्हाट
is it i heard that i think it's
इज इट मैंने सुना है कि आई थिंक के इट्स
chemistry at play chemistry at play
केमिस्ट्री एट प्ले केमिस्ट्री एट प्ले
I personally don't even know biochemistry
बायोकेमिस्ट्री आई आई पर्सनली डोंट इवन नो
exactly how does he do it but it's about
एक्जेक्टली कैसे करता है वो बट इट्स अबाउट
Not editing like the way I said it was cut
नॉट एडिटिंग लाइक द लाइक द आई सेड इट्स कट
copy paste you go in to the genetic code and
कॉपी पेस्ट यू गो इन टू द जेनेटिक कोड एंड
you have the ah adenine tryptophan guanine
यू हैव दी अह एडिनीन ट्रिप्टोफेन ग्वानिन
all this at gct all that code and you can
ये सब एटी जी सी टी ऑल दैट कोड एंड यू कैन
from that over here instead of this ti i want
से कि ओवर हियर इंस्टेड ऑफ़ दिस टी आई वांट
to make it a g and you can actually do it
टू मेक इट अ जी एंड यू कैन एक्चुअली डू इट
So you are saying that that DNA strand
मतलब आप कह रहे हो कि वो डीएनए स्ट्रैंड
There are a lot of things embedded in it.
में बहुत सारी चीजें एंबेडेल्डेड है।
You can take out some things from it.
उसमें से कुछ-कुछ चीजें आप निकाल सकते हो।
You can add some things. can add
कुछ-कुछ चीज़ आप ऐड कर सकते हो। ऐड कर सकते
yes, you can remove it, you can delete it,
हो, निकाल सकते हो, डिलीट कर सकते हो,
You can change it. Whatever you want to do then
चेंज कर सकते हो। जो भी आपको करना है तो
it will work properly if you are precise
इट विल वर्क प्रॉपर्ली अगर आप प्रिसाइजली
it should be exactly what you say
एक्सैक्टली आप जो कहते हो वही हो इट शुड
do not introduce any defective code in
नॉट इंट्रोड्यूस एनी डिफेक्टिव कोड इन
there essentially hmm
देयर एसेंशुअली हम्म
Cancer Prevented Treated Ore Ky Crisper
कैंसर प्रिवेंटेड ट्रीटेड ओर क्य क्रिस्पर
Eradication of genetic diseases like cystic
इरेडिकेशन ऑफ़ जेनेटिक डिजीज लाइक सिस्टिक
Fibrosis in sickle cell disease in adults
फाइब्रोसिस सिकल सेल डिजीज अह एडल्ट्स मे
be able to receive inbody gene editing to
बी एबल टु रिसीव इनबॉडी जीन एडिटिंग टू
Treat and reverse genetic diseases. Wow! We
ट्रीट और रिवर्स जेनेटिक डिजीज। वाह! हम
that's interesting a
दैट्स इंटरेस्टिंग अ
Human beings may be able to get annual
ह्यूमन बीइंग्स मे बी एबल टू गेट एनुअल
Genome health checkup means your own
जीनोम हेल्थ चेकअप यानी कि आपके खुद के
Suppose if there is something wrong with the gene code
जीन कोड में अगर कुछ खराबी है अगर मान लो
You are 20 years old now but your gene code has
आप अभी 20 साल के हो पर आपके जीन कोड में
It is written that my friend might get cancer in the future
ये लिखा है कि यार आगे जाकर शायद कैंसर हो
If possible, it could probably be edited out
सकता है तो वो शायद एडिट आउट हो सकता है
Based on CRISPR technology Anti Aging
बेस्ड ऑन क्रिस्पर टेक्नोलॉजी एंटी एजिंग
And Longevity Therapies which are a huge craze
एंड लोंजेविटी थेरेपीस जो बहुत बड़ा क्रेज
It has been made because of Brian Johnson
बन चुका है ब्राइन जॉनसन की वजह से
there are genes that accelerate aging they could
देयर आर जींस दैट एक्सलरेट एजिंग दे कुड
BB Switched Off and Crisper Might
बी बी स्विच्ड ऑफ अ एंड क्रिसपर माइट
Extend Healthy Life Span to 10 by 10
एक्सटेंड हेल्दी लाइफ स्पैन टू 10 बाय 10
Two 20 years. Hmm. Then it is written Dizer
टू 20 इयर्स। हम्म। फिर लिखा है डिज़र
Babies. We just talked about that. tell me a little
बेबीज। वो हम बात किए थे अभी। बताइए थोड़ा
Till then what is designer babies?
तब तक डिज़ाइनर बेबीज क्या होता है?
Designer babies. So my IQ from Lets
डिज़ाइनर बेबीज। तो मेरा लेट्स से आईक्यू
It is 120. for example this hypothesis
120 है। फॉर एग्जांपल ये हाइपोथ
It is hypothetically. and my wife's too
हाइपोथेटिकली है। और मेरी पत्नी का भी
IQ from lats IQ from lats is 120.
आईक्यू लेट्स से आईक्यू लेट्स से 120 है।
So most likely our children will be
तो मोस्ट लाइकली हमारे जो बच्चे होंगे
His IQ is also around that of others
उनके भी उनका भी आईक्यू उसके आसपास ही
will be. But I've got a kid with a 150 IQ
होगा। लेकिन मुझे 150 आईक्यू वाला बच्चा
Needed So if we
चाहिए। तो अगर हम
can determine which genes determine IQ
डिटरमिन कर सके कि कौन से जींस से आईक्यू
Which other genes can increase IQ?
बढ़ सकता है और कौन से जींस आईक्यू को
can determine then we can tweet those
डिटरमिन कर सकते हैं देन वी कैन ट्वीट दोज़
jeans and i can have a child that is super
जींस एंड आई कैन हैव अ चाइल्ड दैट इज सुपर
Intelligent. And if I want to
इंटेलीजेंट। एंड अगर मैं चाहता हूं कि
My child is double my height or
मेरा बच्चा मुझसे डबल हाइट का हो या
whatever you know you can have any designer
व्हाटएवर यू नो यू कैन हैव एनी डिजाइनर
Characteristics that you want. Batista
कैरेक्टरिस्टिक्स दैट यू वांट। बटिस्टा
Like the body. Yes. Batista as Dave Batista
जैसी बॉडी। हां। बटिस्टा डेव बटिस्टा जैसी
body and einstein like ah brain
बॉडी और आइंस्टाइन जैसा जैसा अह दिमाग
It's kind of a thing.
इट्स ऑफ़ थिंग।
[music]
[संगीत]
ok dear baby ok ek final line di hai
ओके डिज़र बेबी ओके एक फाइनल लाइन दी है
by 2045 chrisor could be curing disease
बाय 2045 क्रिसर कुड बी क्योरिंग डिजीज
Extending Live Designing Trades
एक्सटेंडिंग लाइव डिजाइनिंग ट्रेड्स
redefining biology but it will raise the
रिीडिफाइनिंग बायोलॉजी बट इट विल रेज द
The Most Profound Ethical Questions of the
मोस्ट प्रोफाउंड एथिकल क्वेश्चंस ऑफ द
What does century mean sir, is it ethical?
सेंचुरी मतलब क्या सर हम क्या ये एथिकल है
See, we have evolved through doing all this
ये सब करना देखिए हम इवॉल्व हुए हैं थ्रू
Biology Through Darwinian Selection Theory
बायोलॉजी थ्रू डार्विनियन सिलेक्शन थ्योरी
All that our evolution says is that humans
ऑल दैट हमारा इवोल्यूशन कहता है कि ह्यूमन
Being has a roughly average life span
बीइंग हैज़ अ रफली ली एवरेज लाइफ स्पैन
A typical human being is about 80 years old.
लगभग 80 साल का टिपिकली ह्यूमन बीइंग 80
The year will live. If you are artificially
साल जिएगा। अगर आप आर्टिफिशियली
The life span of the rich people has increased
जो पैसे वाले लोग हैं उनका लाइफ स्पैन बढ़ा
You are because obviously he has a crush on Chris
रहे हो क्योंकि क्रिस पर ऑब्वियसली उसका
There is a price. It's gonna cost some money. every
एक प्राइस है। इट्स गना कॉस्ट सम मनी। हर
No one will be in reach to have the son of
किसी के रीच में नहीं होगा टू हैव द सन ऑफ़
Gene therapy done to them. So those rich people
जीन थेरेपी डन टू देम। तो जो जो धनवान लोग
they will increase their life span, their
हैं वो अपना लाइफ स्पैन बढ़ाएंगे, अपना
Will increase intelligence. Make your kids super smart
इंटेलिजेंस बढ़ाएंगे। अपने बच्चों को सुपर
If you make us intelligent then it is going to
इंटेलिजेंट बनाएंगे तो इट्स गोइंग टू
create a situation where people who have
क्रिएट अ सिचुएशन जहां पर जिन लोगों के
pass for whatever is in paisa nahi hai woh
पास फॉर व्हाटएवर इज़ इन पैसा नहीं है वो
We will become an inferior human race, it's
एक इंफीरियर ह्यूमन रेस बन जाएंगे इट इट्स
Gonna cause a buffering of the human race
गोना कॉज अ बफरर्केशन ऑफ़ द ह्यूमन रेस
into super intelligent super rich people and
इंटू सुपर इंटेलिजेंट सुपर रिच पीपल एंड
poor people who are left behind so ye
पुअर पीपल हु आर लेफ्ट बिहाइंड सो ये
ethical concern is that's one example of
एथिकल कंसर्न है दैट्स वन एग्जांपल ऑफ़
Ethical Concerns on One Side Rich Super
एथिकल कंसर्न एक साइड पे अमीर सुपर
Humans and on the other side the general public yes
ह्यूमंस और बाकी साइड पे एक आम जनता हां
Who is basically just a human being.
जो बेसिकली जस्ट जस्ट एक मनुष्य है।
He is a human being. Yes. I mean you and I right now
मनुष्य है। यस। मतलब आप और मैं भी अभी
They are humans. We are not super humans. So
मनुष्य हैं। हम सुपर ह्यूमंस नहीं है। तो
We will have this ability in our hands
हमारे पास ये एबिलिटी आ जाएगी हमारे हाथ
to transform ourselves into gods
में टू ट्रांसफॉर्म आवरसेल्व्स इंटू गॉड्स
Essentially. We are super humans. Superman.
एसेंशियली। हम सुपर ह्यूमंस। सुपरमैन।
Hmm those who have money can do this
हम्म तो जिनके पास पैसा है वो ये कर
Will find it. Is it ethical? Or everyone gets this chance
पाएंगे। इज इट एथिकल? या फिर सबको ये चांस
Should meet. We are going to launch GPT in 2025 and up
मिलना चाहिए। हम जीपीटी इन 2025 एंड अप
How Expensive Are CRISPRs Till 2030
टिल 2030 हाउ एक्सपेंसिव आर क्रिसपर
Related Treatments Please Give Me An
रिलेटेड ट्रीटमेंट्स प्लीज गिव मी एन
Output in rupees and not dollars
आउटपुट इन रुपीस एंड नॉट डॉलर्स
Realistic Projection for Crisper
रियलिस्टिक प्रोजेक्शन फॉर क्रिस्पर
Related Treatment Cost in India
रिलेटेड ट्रीटमेंट कॉस्ट इन इंडिया
2.5 crore minimum there we go there we go see
ढाई करोड़ मिनिमम देयर वी गो देयर वी गो सी
it right there and this is the most basic one
इट राइट देयर और ये जो सबसे बेसिक वाली
Are these things globally approved?
चीजें हैं ना ग्लोबली अप्रूव्ड
Treatments Like Vertex for Sickle Cell
ट्रीटमेंट्स लाइक वर्टेक्स फॉर सिकल सेल
Anemia hmm cost cost 2.5 to 3.5 crore
एनीमिया हम्म कॉस्ट कॉस्ट 2.5 टू 3.5 करोड़
But patient. there we have it one time
पर पेशेंट। देयर वी हैव इट वन टाइम
Treatment but it will cost that much.
ट्रीटमेंट बट या इट विल कॉस्ट दैट मच।
Wow! There is also a projected cost table
वाह! एक प्रोजेक्टेड कॉस्ट का टेबल भी
has given it. ok where it is written
दिया है। अच्छा अ जहां लिखा है
All this diabetes cancer will be there roughly by 2028
ये सब डायबिटीज कैंसर रफली बाय 2028 देयर
is there a chance it could come down to 25 to 50
इज़ अ चांस इट कुड कम डाउन टू 25 टू 50
Patient at the lax. Ok. bye bye that
लैक्स पर पेशेंट। ठीक है। बाय बाय बाय दैट
Time. Yes. But It's Still Limited Access
टाइम। हां। बट इट स्टिल लिमिटेड एक्सेस
Early adopters only. hmm there we have
अर्ली अडॉप्टर्स ओनली। हम्म देयर वी हैव
It. so eventually as time goes by yours jo
इट। सो इवेंचुअली एस टाइम गोज़ बाय आपका जो
The cost of the treatment will go down
ट्रीटमेंट है उसका कॉस्ट कम होता जाएगा
Still but it's gonna be a price
फिर भी लेकिन इट्स गोना बी अ प्राइस
Barriers are obvious and not everyone can afford it
बैरियर ऑब्वियसली और हर कोई अफोर्ड नहीं
will be able to do it or it is saying by 2030 there is
कर पाएगा या इट्स सेइंग बाय 2030 देयर इज़
A chance middle class Indian may be able to
अ चांस मिडिल क्लास इंडियन मे बी एबल टू
Afford Basic CRISPR Based Disease
अफोर्ड बेसिक क्रिस्पर बेस्ड डिजीज
Correction we especially with health insurance
करेक्शन हम एस्पेशली विद हेल्थ इंश्योरेंस
Reforms ok there might be a make in
रिफॉर्म्स ओके देयर माइट बी अ मेक इन
india biotech scale up make good in
इंडिया बायोटेक स्केल अप अच्छा मेक इन
India CRISPER Prime Minister CRISPER
इंडिया क्रिसपर प्रधानमंत्री क्रिसपर
plan yes im sure something like this crisper
योजना हां आई एम श्योर कुछ कुछ तो क्रिसपर
What might be going on in our country? I am not
का चल रहा होगा हमारे देश में। आई एम नॉट
Aware of it. If something like this is going on.
अवेयर ऑफ इट। अगर ऐसा कुछ चल रहा है तो।
But Creeper is a technology, right?
पर क्रिपर एक टेक्नोलॉजी है ना।
There is technology. Yes. So, this technology
टेक्नोलॉजी है। जी। तो इस टेक्नोलॉजी के
Many companies can be formed above. can become
ऊपर काफी सारी कंपनीज़ बन सकता है। बन सकती
Is. Of course. Ok. who invented it
है। ऑफ कोर्स। ओके। इन्वेंट किसने किया
Was? I don't remember. I think there was a lady
था? मुझे याद नहीं है। आई थिंक एक लेडी थी
Perhaps. Ok. But roughly in that range. So
शायद। ओके। बट रफली इन दैट रेंज। तो
The minimum expenditure would be Rs 30 lakh. if at all
मिनिमम 30 लाख का खर्चा होगा। अगर एकदम
If you want a basic crisper treatment
बेसिक वाली क्रिस्पर ट्रीटमेंट चाहिए तो
Too. Yes absolutely. Ok. Should we move on?
भी। जी बिल्कुल। ओके। शुड वी मूव ऑन?
Let's move on. This is a speed podcast.
लेट्स मूव ऑन। स्पीड वाला पडकास्ट है ये।
Ok. 2030
ओके। 2030
Home Robots Developed Emotional Intelligence
होम रोबोट्स डेवलप्ड इमोशनल इंटेलिजेंस
What do you mean? Meaning, if you make your robot
मतलब क्या? मतलब अगर आप अगर अपने रोबोट को
say let's have a robot that
कहेंगे लेट्स से आपके पास एक रोबोट है जो
does your sweeping and mopping,
आपका स्वीपिंग करता है, मॉपिंग करता है,
He sweeps and mops you, does your cooking,
झाड़ू पोछा करता है, आपका कुकिंग करता है,
Chop your onions, stop chopping the cucumber
आपका अनियंस चॉप करता है, कक्कंबर स्टॉप
He does. So bye 20-30 he is saying this, his
करता है। तो बाय 20-30 ये कह रहा है, उसके
The emotions will come. He will have feelings. If
इमोशंस आ जाएंगे। उसकी भावनाएं होंगी। अगर
If you tell him to do his work quickly, he
आप उसे कहेंगे कि भाई जल्दी काम कर तो वो
He will cry. we and so on do you want this
रोएगा। हम एंड सो ऑन क्या आप चाहते हो ऐसा
Robot
रोबोट
Will he be able to read your emotions here?
यहां क्या वो आपके इमोशंस पढ़ पाएगा कि
Friend, my boss is not happy today. If your
यार आज मेरे मालिक खुश नहीं है। अगर आपका
let's have a dog if you have a dog then that
लेट्स से एक डॉग है आपका एक डॉगी है तो वो
He understands your emotions the day you are happy
आपके इमोशन समझता है जिस दिन आप खुश हो तो
He also becomes happy. the day you are sad
वो भी खुश होता है। जिस दिन आप दुखी हो तो
it will console you maybe like this
आपको आपको कंसोल करेगा तो शायद उस प्रकार
the ability to read the emotions of
की भावनाओं को रीड करने की एबिलिटी इन
It will come in robots. Another Thought
रोबोट्स में आ जाएगी। एक और थॉट
Do some experimenting. Absolutely. Ok. Hi
एक्सपेरिमेंट कर लें। बिल्कुल। ओके। हाय
GPT Are You Emotionally Intelligent Now
जीपीटी क्या आप अभी इमोशनली इंटेलिजेंट हो
Answer in Hindi for a human being
हिंदी में जवाब दीजिए एक ह्यूमन बीइंग की
Tell me five quickly with ams and ass
तरह अम्स और अस्स के साथ बताइए झट से पांच
In Sentences
सेंटेंसेस में
Look, I'm an AI, so I have
देखिए मैं तो एक एआई हूं तो मेरे पास
They don't have emotions like humans do, but
इंसानों की तरह इमोशंस नहीं होते लेकिन
I am trying to understand your points and respond to them
मैं आपकी बातों को समझने और उनका जवाब
I take your feelings into consideration while giving.
देने में आपकी भावनाओं का ध्यान रखता हूं।
I mean, as we're talking right now, I
मतलब जैसे अभी हम बात कर रहे हैं तो मैं
I try to make it comfortable for you and
कोशिश करता हूं कि वह आपके लिए सहज और
Be relevant. But my way of talking
प्रासंगिक हो। पर मेरे बात करने के तरीके
So do you understand my feelings?
से आप मेरे जज्बात समझते हो?
yes your tone of voice, your choice of words
हां आपके बोलने के लहजे, शब्दों के चुनाव
And from the questions I can guess that you
और सवालों से एक अंदाजा लगाता हूं कि आप
What mood are you in or what emotions are you going through
किस मूड में हैं या किन भावनाओं से गुजर
have been. then answer accordingly
रहे हैं। फिर उसी के मुताबिक जवाब देने की
I will try. I apply it. I don't apply it.
कोशिश करता हूं। लगाती हूं। लगाता नहीं।
I understood your feelings and their meaning
समझ गई आपकी भावनाओं को समझने और उनका
I try my best to take care. Ok.
ख्याल रखने की पूरी कोशिश करती हूं। ओके।
This is where you printed the document
यह जो आपने डॉक्यूमेंट प्रिंट करी थी जहां
You Said Home Robots Develop Emotions
आपने कहा होम रोबोट्स डेवलप इमोशनल
Intelligence
इंटेलिजेंस
Explain three sentences related to this. You
इससे रिलेटेड तीन सेंटेंसेस समझाइए। आप
what are you trying to say and then this
क्या कहने की कोशिश कर रहे हो और फिर यह
Also tell me if there is any such company in the world
भी बताइए कि दुनिया में ऐसी कोई कंपनीज़ है
Which home robots are already developing
जो होम रोबोट्स अभी ऑलरेडी डेवप कर रही
Is. And also tell me that a home for Rs.
है। और यह भी बताइए कि रुपीस में एक होम
How much will the robot cost? which is absolutely top
रोबोट का खर्चा कितना होगा? जो एकदम टॉप
Off the line home robot will be hers in 2030
ऑफ द लाइन होम रोबोट होगा 2030 में उसका
What will be its price?
खर्चा उसकी प्राइस क्या होगी?
Absolutely. So home robots develop emotions
बिल्कुल। तो होम रोबोट्स डेवलप इमोशनल
Intelligence means that future domestic
इंटेलिजेंस का मतलब है कि भविष्य के घरेलू
Robots will not only do work, but
रोबोट्स सिर्फ काम ही नहीं करेंगे बल्कि
Will also understand our emotional signals.
हमारे भावनात्मक संकेतों को भी समझेंगे।
Meaning if you are happy, sad or tired
मतलब अगर आप खुश हैं, उदास हैं या थके हुए
If yes, then it will react according to your need
हैं तो वह आपकी जरूरत के हिसाब से रिएक्ट
do. Now there are many companies in the world like this
करेंगे। अब दुनिया में कई कंपनियां ऐसे
Working on home robots. Such as
होम रोबोट्स पर काम कर रही हैं। जैसे कि
Boston Dynamics, Soft Bank Robotics
बॉस्टन डायनामिक्स, सॉफ्ट बैंक रोबोटिक्स
Or for paper and Amazon Astro Robot
या पेपर के लिए और Amazon एस्ट्रो रोबोट
For. These companies are making robots more
के लिए। यह कंपनियां रोबोट्स को और
Smart, useful and emotionally intelligent
स्मार्ट, उपयोगी और इमोशनली इंटेलिजेंट
She is busy making it. now if top of the line
बनाने में जुटी है। अब अगर टॉप ऑफ द लाइन
If we talk about home robots, by 2030 such
होम रोबोट की बात करें तो 2030 तक ऐसे
The cost of robots can be between 20 to 30 lakhs
रोबोट्स की कीमत 20 से 30 लाख तक हो सकती
which depends on their features and brand
है जो उनके फीचर्स और ब्रांड पर निर्भर
Will do it. And the most basic robots
करेगा। और जो सबसे बेसिक वाले रोबोट्स
What will be their cost? The cheap ones.
होंगे उनकी कॉस्ट क्या होगी? सस्ते वाले।
The most basic of robots include limited
सबसे बेसिक वाले रोबोट्स जिनमें लिमिटेड
There will be features like household chores and basics
फीचर्स होंगे जैसे घरेलू काम और बेसिक
Interaction Their value will be around 5 to 10 by 2030
इंटरेक्शन उनकी कीमत 2030 तक लगभग 5 से 10
It could be lakhs. These robots are common household
लाख हो सकती है। ये रोबोट्स सामान्य घरेलू
be designed for use and
उपयोग के लिए डिजाइन किए जाएंगे और
An affordable option for early adopters
शुरुआती अडॉप्टर्स के लिए एक अफोर्डेबल
There will be options. It will basically be like a car.
ऑप्शन होंगे। बेसिकली गाड़ी की तरह होंगे।
Home robots means basic ones cost Rs 5 lakh
होम रोबोट्स मतलब बेसिक वाले 5 लाख के
The expensive ones cost Rs 30 lakh. Of 30 lakhs. Yeah.
महंगे वाले 30 लाख के। 30 लाख के। याह।
Tyres. Price in different tyres
टायर्स। अलग-अलग टायर्स में प्राइस
I will get it. but i also feel if its 30 lakhs
मिलेगी। बट आई आल्सो फील अगर 30 लाख के
There will be robots, people will buy them. I Mean
रोबोट्स होंगे, लोग खरीद लेंगे। आई मीन
It's going to make a life much easy. one time
इट्स गोइंग टु मेकअ लाइफ मच ईजी। वन टाइम
There is investment. Yes. in it automatically
इन्वेस्टमेंट है। हां। उसमें अपने आप ऑटो
Software updates will come. battery in it
अपडेट्स आएंगी सॉफ्टवेयर की। उसमें बैटरी
It will be. So, there will be some running charge for it.
होगी। सो, कुछ तो रनिंग चार्ज होगा उसका।
but overall i think it's a one time
बट ओवरऑल आई थिंक इट्स अ वन टाइम
Investment. Do you think it will be 20-30 years
इन्वेस्टमेंट। क्या आपको लगता है 20-30 तक
Will this become the actual reality? it is possibile
ये एक्चुअल रियलिटी बन जाएगी? पॉसिबल है
because at this time you will see that robotics
क्योंकि इस समय आप आप देखेंगे कि रोबोटिक
The development that is going on in technological
डेवलपमेंट जो चल रही है टेक्नोलॉजिकल
The development is quite good. some robots
डेवलपमेंट काफी अच्छी है। कुछ-कुछ रोबोट्स
These are the ones who are mimicking the humans
ऐसे हैं व्हिच आर मिमिकिंग द ह्यूमन
muscular skeletal structure all the same which
मस्कुल स्केलेटल स्ट्रक्चर वही सारे जो जो
We have muscles in our body in the same way
हमारे मसल्स हैं बॉडी में उसी प्रकार से
They have been designed. and quite agile
उनको डिजाइन किया गया है। और काफी अजाइल
There are robots. so i think by 2030 this
रोबोट्स हैं। सो आई थिंक बाय 2030 ये
There is definitely a possibility.
डेफिनेटली पॉसिबिलिटी है।
a i think it was kawasaki na kawasaki ne
अ आई थिंक इट वास कावासाकी ना कावासाकी ने
A new horse yes that robotic horse released
एक नया हॉर्स हां वो रोबोटिक हॉर्स रिलीज
The video I generated was actually really good
आई जनरेटेड वीडियो था एक्चुअली अच्छा रियल
it is not real it is not real but
नहीं है रियल नहीं है रियल नहीं है बट
Is it a concept or a concept I think it is basic
कांसेप्ट है या कांसेप्ट आई थिंक बेसिक
The concept has been made, I think they have a
कांसेप्ट बन चुका है आई थिंक दे हैव अ
Basic prototype but so much capability
बेसिक प्रोटोटाइप लेकिन उतना कैपेबिलिटी
It doesn't have it yet I think that's on AI
उसमें अभी नहीं है आई थिंक दैट्स ऑन एआई
Generated video but very good concept
जनरेट वीडियो लेकिन बहुत अच्छा कांसेप्ट
hay i would like to have one of this or
है आई वुड लाइक टू हैव है वन ऑफ़ दिस या
Go for a small walk on a nice track
जाओ मस्त ट्रैक पे घूमो एक छोटे से
Absolutely ok next with a robotic horse
रोबोटिक घोड़े के साथ बिलकुल ओके नेक्स्ट
Next Update of 2030 Organ Printing
नेक्स्ट अपडेट ऑफ़ 2030 ऑर्गन प्रिंटिंग
Hits main stream hospitals. Hum Organ
हिट्स मेन स्ट्रीम हॉस्पिटल्स। हम ऑर्गन
what is printing sir? You have 3D
प्रिंटिंग होती क्या है सर? आपने 3D
You must have heard about printing. To you
प्रिंटिंग के बारे में सुना होगा। आपको
anything from lets to mugs if you
कुछ भी अगर लेट्स से मग को अगर आपको
If you want to print then you can have a 3D
प्रिंट करना है तो यू कैन हैव अ 3D
Printer. You put the dish in it. I think
प्रिंटर। उसमें आप डिज़ डाल दो। आई थिंक
Put the materials and they will print it for you
मटेरियल्स डाल दो एंड वो आपको प्रिंट करके
will give. 3D printed mug or if you want nowadays
देगा। 3D प्रिंटेड मग या फिर आपको आजकल तो
I heard that you can also print AR15 rifles
मैं सुना है कि AR15 राइफल भी आप प्रिंट
You can do it. so now soft tissue
कर सकते हो। तो अभी सॉफ्ट टिश्यू
Printing technology is developing
प्रिंटिंग का टेक्नोलॉजी बन रहा है
Apparently. So this is saying that by 2030
अपेरेंटली। तो ये कह रहा है कि बाय 2030
You can use human heart, human liver or whatever
आप ह्यूमन हार्ट, ह्यूमन लिवर या जो भी
Complex Bio Biological Structures
कॉम्प्लेक्स बायो बायोलॉजिकल स्ट्रक्चर्स
you will be able to print it and in that you
है उसको आप प्रिंट कर पाओगे और उसमें आप
You will be able to give your DNA so that your body
अपना डीएनए दे पाओगे ताकि आपका बॉडी के
If you want to insert that organ inside then
अंदर अगर आपको वो ऑर्ड ऑर्गन डालना है तो
your body's immune system
आपका बॉडी का जो इम्यून सिस्टम है उसको
Don't reject it. He should consider it as his part.
रिजेक्ट ना करे। वो अपना ही हिस्सा समझे।
If we see what happens today, someone is late
हम अगर देखिए आज क्या होता है किसी का लेट
liver failure or someone's heart
से लिवर फेल हो गया या किसी को हार्ट
If there is a failure then they need an organ
फेलियर हो रहा है तो उनको एक ऑर्गन
Someone else's transplant has to be done
ट्रांसप्लांट करना पड़ता है किसी और का
organ that has died
ऑर्गन जो जिसकी मृत्यु हो चुकी होती है
They take his organ and put it inside. and this
उसका ऑर्गन लेके अंदर डालते हैं। और ये
I would like to tell the audience that as many
मैं ऑडियंस को कहना चाहूंगा कि जितने भी
I have talked to the doctor
डॉक्टर से बात हुई है ऑर्गन
This is about transplants in India
ट्रांसप्लांट्स के बारे में ये भारत में
It has become a huge problem because
एक बहुत बड़ा प्रॉब्लम बन चुका है क्योंकि
There are very few organ donors in our country.
हमारे देश में ऑर्गन डोनर्स बहुत कम है।
It is very little. So if someone actually
बहुत कम है। तो अगर किसी को एक्चुअली
I need organs, I need heart, I need liver,
ऑर्गन चाहिए, हार्ट चाहिए, लिवर चाहिए,
You need eyes, this is a very difficult challenge
आंखें चाहिए, ये एक बहुत मुश्किल चैलेंज
It happens for the common Indian. yes absolutely
होता है आम भारतीय के लिए। जी बिल्कुल
Absolutely. I believe there are cues. Very
बिल्कुल। आई बिलीव क्यूस होते हैं। बहुत
There are long queues. There are long queues.
लंबे क्यू होते हैं। लंबे क्यू होते हैं।
Yes. The demand is very high and the supply is very high
यस। डिमांड बहुत ज्यादा है और सप्लाई बहुत
It is less. what we are now is that if you
कम है। हम तो अभी क्या है कि अगर आप किसी
What organ do you take? Your kidneys fail due to late
का ऑर्गन लेते हो आपका लेट्स से किडनी फेल
It has happened. You had to take someone's kidney. So
हुआ है। आपको किसी का किडनी लेना पड़ा। तो
This kidney's genetic code is from someone else
ये किडनी का जो जेनेटिक कोड है वो किसी और
It is of. So your body's immune system
का है। तो आपका जो बॉडी का इम्यून सिस्टम
he will consider it a foreign object and
है वो उसे फॉरेन ऑब्जेक्ट समझेगा और उसको
attempts to destroy it and if such
नष्ट करने का प्रयत्न करेगा और अगर ऐसा
If it happens then in one month whatever organ you have
हुआ तो एकद महीने में वो जो आपने ऑर्गन
It will be destroyed and you will have to do the same thing again
लिया वो नष्ट हो जाएगा और आपको फिर से वही
the problem will be that you have lost a
प्रॉब्लम हो जाएगा कि यू हैव लॉस्ट अ
kidney. You don't have any kidney left. So
किडनी। यू डोंट हैव एनी किडनी लेफ्ट। तो
For that you need to take anti rejection drugs.
उसके लिए आपको एंटी रिजेक्शन ड्रग्स लेने
which affects your immune system
पड़ते हैं जो आपके इम्यून सिस्टम को
It suppresses and that gives you no relief from the lettuce
सप्रेस करता है और उससे आपको लेट्स से कोई
You will suffer from minor illnesses too
छोटी-मोटी बीमारी होगी उससे भी आपकी
Death may occur. So if you have seen a 3D organ
मृत्यु हो सकती है। तो अगर आपने 3D ऑर्गन
Print it out and put your DNA in it
प्रिंट किया और अपना डीएनए उसमें डाल दिया
Your genetic code is your own organ
अपना जेनेटिक कोड तो वो आपका ही ऑर्गन हो
and you have any immune suppressing medicine
गया और आपको ऐसा कोई इम्यून सप्रेसिंग
You will not have to take any medicine. These
मेडिसिन मेडिसिन नहीं लेना पड़ेगा। ये
There will be a huge revolutionary change. when these
बहुत बड़ा रेवोल्यूशनरी चेंज होगा। जब ये
It happens. If we are around 2030 then this will happen
होता है। हम तो अगर 2030 के आसपास ये हो
If it goes then the richest people will be its
गया तो जो सबसे अमीर लोग होंगे वो इसका
You will be able to avail the benefit first. We this too
सबसे पहले बेनिफिट ले पाएंगे। हम ये भी
It would be somewhere in the range of Rs 25-30 lakh. I think
कुछ 25 30 लाख के रेंज में होगा। आई थिंक
possible ok moving on
पॉसिबल ओके मूविंग ऑन
2035 AI assistants begin replacing
2035 एआई असिस्टेंट्स बिगेन रिप्लेसिंग
White collar jobs.
वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स।
What does white collar mean? white collar means you
वाइट कॉलर मतलब क्या? वाइट कॉलर मतलब आप
You are not working on the road. You
रोड पर काम नहीं कर रहे हो। आप
You are not doing construction. you in the office
कंस्ट्रक्शन नहीं कर रहे हो। आप ऑफिस में
Sitting in a small AC cubicle
बैठकर एसी क्यूबिकल में एक छोटे से
You are working in a cubicle. thats
क्यूबिकल में आप काम कर रहे हो। दैट्स
White collar jobs. basically in today's days you
वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स। बेसिकली इन टुडेज डेज यू
Can you say if you are working with a computer.
कैन से इफ यू वर्किंग विथ अ कंप्यूटर।
Computer Intellectual Work. Yes. Brain
कंप्यूटर इंटेलेक्चुअल वर्क। यस। दिमाग
are you thinking or are you his manager
दिमाग कर रहे हो या फिर आप उसके मैनेजर
Stay tuned, Project Manager wherever you're talking to
रहो, प्रोजेक्ट मैनेजर होएवर यू टॉकिंग टू
People, you are inside a building. you have no
पीपल यू आर इनसाइड अ बिल्डिंग। आपको कोई
There is no need to do manual labour. it's
मैनुअल लेबर नहीं करना पड़ रहा है। इट्स
Intellectual work mainly on computers.
इंटेलेक्चुअल वर्क मेनली ऑन कंप्यूटरटर्स।
This is called a white collar job. so I am saying this
इसे वाइट कॉलर जॉब कहते हैं। तो ये कह रहा
That by 2035 AI assistance will start
है कि बाय 2035 एआई असिस्टेंस विल स्टार्ट
Replacing white collar jobs. I so say
रिप्लेसिंग वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स। मैं तो कह
I am doing it, it will happen from today. It's already happening.
रहा हूं आज से होगा। इट्स ऑलरेडी हैपनिंग।
From I Wood. If you have AI today
आई वुड से। अगर आपका आज आपके पास एआई
Agents are the ones who create your software
एजेंट्स है जो आपके आपका सॉफ्टवेयर बना
Can be done. If you look at today's
सकते हैं। अगर आप देखिए आजकल कौन सी
Technology cursor is for example which
टेक्नोलॉजी कर्सर है फॉर एग्जांपल व्हिच
Can write any code. I heard that Claude
कैन राइट एनी कोड। मैं सुना है कि क्लॉड
Even if you tell someone to give a link to a website
को भी अगर आप बोलेंगे एक वेबसाइट का लिंक
Give it to them and you tell Claude to tell me
दीजिए उनको और आप क्लड को बोलिए कि मुझे
You need such a website within a few
ऐसा वेबसाइट चाहिए आपको विदिन अ फ्यू
In minutes I am sure the whole code is ready
मिनट्स आई एम श्योर पूरा का पूरा कोड बना
that he will give you ₹1 lakh right now
के देगा वो तो आपको अभी जो ₹1 लाख आपको
Had to pay someone to make the website
किसी को देने पड़ते थे वेबसाइट बना के
You are getting it for free today to make
बनाने के लिए आज आपको फ्री में मिल रहा है
All you have to do is ask him whether he
वो आपको सिर्फ ये पूछना है उसको कि उसको
how do i implement you are playing clud
मैं इंप्लीमेंट कैसे करूं आप खेले हो क्लड
GPT Deep See How I Used GPT
जीपीटी डीप सी कैसे मैंने जीपीटी का यूज़
I have done Claude and Deepsea so far
किया है क्लॉड और डीपसी का मैंने अभी तक
We haven't used it, we mean the audience
प्रयोग नहीं किया है हम मतलब ऑडियंस को
I would like to give a suggestion. I play a lot
मैं एक सजेशन देना चाहूंगा। मैं बहुत खेल
I have been with AIS. it's a healthy
रहा हूं एआईएस के साथ। इट्स अ हेल्दी
Practice to play with threes and fours. Three
प्रैक्टिस टू प्ले विद थ्री और फोर। थ्री
and Four of This. Yes. because different
और फोर ऑफ़ दिस। हां। क्योंकि अलग-अलग
There are strengths. different for each one
स्ट्रेंथ्स होते हैं। हर एक के अलग-अलग
There are biases. and you should play
बायसेस होते हैं। और आपको खेलना चाहिए
Biases should be tested with them.
उनके साथ बायसेस टेस्ट करने चाहिए।
Political opinions should be asked. ask this
पॉलिटिकल ओपिनियंस पूछने चाहिए। ये पूछना
what should you say about humans
चाहिए कि आप इंसानों के बारे में क्या
Do you think so? What do you think about society?
सोचते हो? आप समाज के बारे में क्या सोच?
I think I saw this one a few months ago
आई थिंक हमने कुछ महीनों पहले ये एक
Had used it. Right? We've read Vinson Churchill
प्रयोग किया था। राइट? हमने विंसन चर्चिल
I had asked about it. Something had done like this.
के बारे में पूछा था। कुछ तो ऐसा किया था।
and some other way of doing it is the same work
एंड सम अनदर वे ऑफ़ डूइंग इट इज सेम वर्क
Give flow instructions to every AI. They
फ्लो के इंस्ट्रश हर एक एआई को दे दो। वो
Will implement it differently. Yes. and you
अलग-अलग से इम्लीमेंट करेगा। हां। एंड यू
will be able to tell whether this task is good or not
विल बी एबल टू टेल कि अच्छा इस टास्क के
Maybe a clot is better for that. this task
लिए शायद क्लॉट ज्यादा अच्छा है। इस टास्क
Deep seek is better for this etc.
के लिए डीप सीक ज्यादा अच्छा है वगैरह।
Ok. This is what you have written in the 2035 section
ओके। ये जो आपने लिखा है 2035 के सेक्शन
AI assistants begin replacing
में एआई असिस्टेंट्स बिगिन रिप्लेसिंग
White collar jobs. can you please give me this
वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स। क्या आप प्लीज मुझे ये
Can you tell me five such white collar jobs?
बता सकते हो कुछ ऐसे पांच वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स
Which will definitely replace you according to you?
जो पक्का रिप्लेस होंगे आपके अकॉर्डिंग?
yes, by 2035 some white collar jobs which
हां तो 2035 तक कुछ वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स जो
There is every possibility of being replaced by AI
एआई से रिप्लेस होने की पूरी संभावना है
He is a data entry clerk, this job is
वो है एक डाटा एंट्री क्लर्क यह काम
Can be done faster with automation.
ऑटोमेशन से तेजी से किया जा सकता है।
Second Translators Language Translation Now AI
दूसरा ट्रांसलेटर्स भाषा अनुवाद अब एआई
The tools are easy to do. Third Customer
टूल्स आसानी से कर रहे हैं। तीसरा कस्टमर
Service Representatives Chatbus and
सर्विस रिप्रेजेंटेटिव्स चैटब्स और
Virtual assistants are taking their place.
वर्चुअल असिस्टेंट्स इनकी जगह ले रहे हैं।
Fourth, bookkeepers, accounting softwares and
चौथा बुककीपर्स, अकाउंटिंग सॉफ्टवेयर्स और
AI doing financial analysis
एआई फाइनेंसियल एनालिसिस का काम कर रहे
Are. Fifth Research Analysts, Data
हैं। पांचवा रिसर्च एनालिस्ट्स, डाटा
Processing and report generation now with AI
प्रोसेसिंग और रिपोर्ट जनरेशन अब एआई से
It has become very fast. I think so
बहुत तेज हो गया है। मैं तो सोचता हूं कि
Lots of white collar jobs right now
काफी सारा वाइट कॉलर जॉब्स अभी अभी से
It will start replacing. The Examples
रिप्लेस होना शुरू हो जाएगा। द एग्जांपल्स
The information they have given is quite valid
जो उन्होंने दिए हैं वो काफी वैलिड है ऑफ
Course. but programmers programmers
कोर्स। लेकिन प्रोग्रामर्स प्रोग्रामर्स
It will be replaced from today itself. so ye bye
आज से ही रिप्लेस हो जाएंगे। सो ये बाय
2035 so I think all of them will be white collar workers
2035 तो आई थिंक सारे के सारे वाइट कॉलर्स
Jobs would be under threat by that time.
जॉब्स वुड बी अंडर थ्रेट बाय दैट टाइम।
Hmm. Definitely there is a possibility. See the I Think
हम्। डेफिनेटली संभावना है। सी द आई थिंक
The one guarantee is your job profile is fully
द वन गारंटी इज़ आपकी जॉब प्रोफाइल फुल्ली
It will become moldy. This is an old AI base
मोल्ड हो जाएगी। यह एक पुराना एआई बेस
The narrative is that the person who uses AI
नैरेटिव है कि जिस इंसान को एआई को यूज़
Does one know how to do it or does one who has learnt it have more
करना आता है या जिसने सीख लिया वो ज्यादा
will move forward. Absolutely. See Technological
आगे बढ़ेगा। बिल्कुल। देखिए टेक्नोलॉजिकल
Progress has always been happening. and who
प्रोग्रेस तो हमेशा से होता रहा है। और जो
People Embrace Technological Progress
लोग टेक्नोलॉजिकल प्रोग्रेस को एंब्रेस
and adopt new technologies with enthusiasm
करते हैं और नई टेक्नोलॉजीस को अह के साथ
They adapt. Those people will thrive.
अडैप्ट होते हैं। वो लोग थ्राइव करेंगे।
I didn't tell anyone I think Sharan Jaan Finance
मैंने ना किसी को आई थिंक शरण जान फाइनेंस
With Sharan. So I was talking to him.
विथ शरण। सो उनसे बात हो रही थी मेरी।
He told me that these Big Four
उन्होंने मुझे ये कहा था कि ये जो बिग फोर
The companies are EY, Deloitte, KPMG
कंपनीज़ हैं ईवाई, डेलइट, KPMG ये इनके
Many job profiles will change
बहुत सारे जॉब प्रोफाइल्स चेंज होंगे
Because they are basically consulting firms
क्योंकि दे आर बेसिकली कंसल्टिंग फर्म्स
Yes. Right now this whole consulting world is
यस। अभी ये पूरी कंसल्टिंग की दुनिया इट्स
Going to be kind of redirected
गोइंग टू बी काइंड ऑफ रीडायरेक्टेड
Towards AI Agents. Yes yes. then i know that
टुवर्ड्स एआई एजेंट्स। यस यस। तो आई नो कि
There are a lot of changes in the corporate world.
कॉर्पोरेट वर्ल्ड में बहुत सारे चेंजेस
Will come. Nowadays I have heard that AI systems
आएंगे। आजकल मैंने सुना है कि एआई सिस्टम
like chatty some deep research in it something like that
लाइक चैटिटी उसमें कुछ डीप रिसर्च ऐसा कुछ
So a feature has come which is essentially an I think
तो फीचर आया है जो एसेंशियली एक आई थिंक
PhD level analyst works at the end
पीएचडी लेवल एनालिस्ट का काम करता है एंड
That is very long and very detailed to you.
वो आपको बहुत लंबा बहुत डिटेल्ड बहुत
will give you an accurate report which you
एक्यूरेट रिपोर्ट देगा जिसको आप आपको
Fact check will have to be done but essentially
फैक्ट चेक तो करना पड़ेगा लेकिन एसेंशुअली
If you are a lawyer, you have your law form.
अगर आप लॉयर हैं आपके आपकी लॉ फ़ॉर्म है।
In that case you have 20 employees. You
उसमें लेट से आपके पास 20 एंप्लोईस है। आप
Essentially you can give the same work to AI. Give
एसेंशियली वही काम एआई को दे सकते हो। दे
will do a much better job much faster you
विल डू अ मच बेटर जॉब मच फास्टर आपको
But to do fact checking, people
लेकिन फैक्ट चेकिंग करने के लिए लोगों को
We will have to employ legal research
एंप्लॉय करना पड़ेगा हम सो लीगल रिसर्च
If you have a big case, it is a legal case
आपके पास अगर बड़ा केस है लीगल केस है एक
If something is going on with the company then
कंपनी के के साथ कुछ चल रहा है तो उसके
Its documentation is very voluminous
उसका डॉक्यूमेंटेशन बहुत वॉल्यूमस होता है
thousands of pages of documents and that
थाउजेंड्स ऑफ़ पेजेस ऑफ़ डॉक्यूमेंट्स और उस
Your assistants read all this.
आपके जो असिस्टेंट्स है वो यही सब पढ़ते
and they have to do pass through all the
रहते हैं एंड दे हैव टू डू पास थ्रू ऑल द
Documentation so AI can do this now very much
डॉक्यूमेंटेशन तो एआई कैन डू दिस नाउ वैरी
fast ok gbt i would like to know that
फास्ट ओके जीबीटी मैं ये जानना चाहूंगा कि
I have heard that there are Big Four companies.
मैंने सुना है बिग फोर कंपनीज़ है ना पहले
So tell me the names of those big four companies. Then
तो वो बिग फोर कंपनीज़ के नाम बताइए। फिर
tell me that according to you and your deep
यह बताइए कि आपके अकॉर्डिंग और आपके डीप
Research
रिसर्च
Are there many jobs because of this feature?
फीचर की वजह से क्या काफी सारे जॉब्स
Will be replaced in Big Four companies and
रिप्लेस हो जाएंगे बिग फोर कंपनीज में और
If yes, then when? Tell me the truth objectively.
अगर हां तो कब अ सच-सच बताइए ऑब्जेक्टिवली
Ofcourse the big four companies are EY
बिल्कुल तो बिग फोर कंपनियां है इवाई
Ernst Young Deloitte KPMG and PwC
अर्st यंग डिलॉइ केपीएमजी और पीडब्ल्यूसी
Price Water House Coopers these companies
प्राइस वाटर हाउस कूपर्स ये कंपनियां
Mainly Consulting, Auditing and
मुख्य रूप से कंसल्टिंग ऑडिटिंग और
Working in financial services, now working on AI
फाइनेंसियल सर्विज में काम करती अब एआई के
There will definitely be some jobs in these companies after coming
आने से इन कंपनियों में कुछ जॉब्स जरूर
Will be replaced. especially data analysis,
रिप्लेस होंगे। खासकर डाटा एनालिसिस,
in Auditing and Basic Consulting. AI
ऑडिटिंग और बेसिक कंसल्टिंग में। एआई
Tools can process data faster
टूल्स तेजी से डाटा प्रोसेस कर सकते हैं
And can provide deeper insights. By which
और गहराई से इनसाइट्स दे सकते हैं। जिससे
Reduced need for multiple existing profiles
कई मौजूदा प्रोफाइल्स की जरूरत कम हो
will go. To be honest, in the next 5 to 10 years
जाएगी। सच-सच बताऊं तो अगले 5 से 10 सालों
This change will become clearly visible. Especially 2030.
में यह बदलाव साफ दिखने लगेगा। खासकर 2030
By now these companies will fully integrate AI
तक यह कंपनियां एआई को पूरी तरह इंटीग्रेट
will do it and change the profile of many jobs
कर लेंगी और कई जॉब्स का प्रोफाइल बदल
Will go. answer in hindi how many
जाएगा। हिंदी में जवाब दीजिए हाउ मेनी
Percentage of jobs will be replaced in the
परसेंटेज ऑफ जॉब्स विल बी रिप्लेस्ड इन द
The Big Four?
बिग फोर?
In the next 10 years, the Big Four companies will
अगले 10 सालों में बिग फोर कंपनियों में
About 30 to 40% of jobs will change due to AI
करीब 30 से 40% जॉब्स एआई के कारण बदल
Can be done. means either it is completely
सकते हैं। मतलब या तो वो पूरी तरह से
will be automated or their work will
ऑटोमेट हो जाएंगे या फिर उनका काम करने का
The method will change completely.
तरीका पूरी तरह से बदल जाएगा।
Will MBS remain relevant in the coming 510?
क्या एमबीएस रेलेवेंट रहेंगे आने वाले 510
In years?
सालों में?
Yes, MBS will still be relevant but
हां, एमबीएस अभी भी रेलेवेंट रहेंगे लेकिन
Their focus will change. next 5 to 10 years
उनका फोकस बदलेगा। आने वाले 5 से 10 सालों
MBA graduates are trained in AI, data,
में एमबीए ग्रेजुएट्स को एआई, डाटा
Business with Analytics and Technology
एनालिटिक्स और टेक्नोलॉजी के साथ बिजनेस
More attention will have to be paid to strategies.
स्ट्रेटजीस पर ज्यादा ध्यान देना होगा।
Meaning technology with traditional skills
मतलब ट्रेडिशनल स्किल्स के साथ टेक्नोलॉजी
The need to understand and adopt will increase.
को समझने और अडॉप्ट करने की जरूरत बढ़ेगी।
aw ok now tell me that what you wrote
अ ओके अभी यह बताइए आप कि यह जो आपने लिखा
in the 2035 column that Lanvity Therapies
है 2035 के कॉलम में कि लनविटी थेरेपीस
Extend life by 30 years so I was born
एक्सटेंड लाइफ बाय 30 इयर्स तो मेरा जन्म
It happened in 1993 when was your birthday sir 76 sir
हुआ था 1993 में आपका कब हुआ था सर 76 सर
what happened in 1976 so you have written here
का हुआ था 1976 में तो आपने यहां लिखा है
that longevity replies extend life by 30
कि लॉन्जिविटी रेपीज एक्सटेंड लाइफ बाय 30
years what does this mean can you say this
इयर्स इसका मतलब क्या है क्या आप यह कह
are you sure therapies will be available and if we
रहे हो कि थेरेपीस अवेलेबल होंगी और इफ वी
Can you buy these therapies? Tell me this also. Hindi
कैन बाय दोस थेरेपीस? यह भी बताइए। हिंदी
I answer. if we can buy dos
में जवाब दीजिए। इफ वी कैन बाय दोस
Therapies, what will be the price of these
थेरेपीस, व्हाट विल बी द प्राइस ऑफ दोस
Repis in Rupees? Ok? So long till 2035
रेपीस इन रूपीस? ठीक है? तो 2035 तक लंबी
There may be age-related therapies available that
उम्र वाली थेरेपीस उपलब्ध हो सकती है जो
It can increase our age by 30 years. Their
हमारी उम्र 30 साल तक बढ़ा सकती है। इनका
That means gene editing, stem cells
मतलब है कि जेने एडिटिंग, स्टेम सेल
Therapy or repair of worn out body parts
थेरेपी या बॉडी के पुराने हो चुके हिस्सों
To rejuvenate. If we talk about the price
को फिर से जवा बनाना। कीमत की बात करें तो
These therapies will be expensive in the beginning. Meaning
यह थेरेपीस शुरुआत में महंगी होंगी। मतलब
It can also go from 50 lakhs to 1 crore
50 लाख से 1 करोड़ तक भी जा सकती है
Depending on the type and complexity.
डिपेंडिंग ऑन द टाइप एंड कॉम्प्लेक्सिटी।
The procedures may be somewhat painful, such as
प्रोसीजर्स शायद कुछ दर्दनाक हो जैसे
in technology on injections or surgeries
इंजेक्शंस या सर्जरीज पर टेक्नोलॉजी में
With improvement it may become less painful.
सुधार के साथ यह कम पेनफुल हो सकती हैं।
Now there is a healthy alternative to these therapies.
अब इन थेरेपीस के लिए एक हेल्दी
It is important to maintain your lifestyle
लाइफस्टाइल मेंटेन करना जरूरी होगा
Because it's Longevity Therapy's Lifestyle
क्योंकि यह लॉनजेविटी थेरेपीस लाइफस्टाइल
Work on improving both science and biology
और बायोलॉजी दोनों को सुधारने पर काम
will do it. We would like to tell you something Longevity
करेंगी। हम आप कुछ कहना चाहोगे लोंजेविटी
About the angle. I Think Dionne Johnson
एंगल के बारे में। आई थिंक डायन जॉनसन
Genuinely he started a revolution
जेनुइनली उन्होंने एक रेवोल्यूशन स्टार्ट
I have done it on the world stage. I Think Indian
किया है वर्ल्ड स्टेज पर। आई थिंक भारतीय
Longevity is not often talked about
अक्सर लोंजेविटी के बारे में बातें नहीं
Do. I feel that there is a health revolution too
करते। आई फील कि हेल्थ रेवोल्यूशन भी
Fitness has started in our country now
हमारे देश में अब स्टार्ट हुआ है फिटनेस
and Health Revolution. It's a good thing.
एंड हेल्थ रेवोल्यूशन। अच्छी बात है।
See, lulzivity means increasing our lifespan.
देखिए लल्जविटी मतलब हमारी आयु को बढ़ाना।
If our average is in India I am not sure
अगर हमारा एवरेज भारत में आई एम नॉट श्योर
What longevity! Average life span 70
कितना लॉन्जविटी है। एवरेज लाइफ स्पैन 70
It might be around 70 years in India. So
70 इयर्स के आसपास होगा शायद भारत में। तो
If this increases by 30 years, then the average Indian
अगर ये 30 साल बढ़ गया तो एवरेज भारतीय
The person will live for 100 years. 30 years more add ho
व्यक्ति 100 साल जिएगा। 30 साल अधिक ऐड हो
Will go. How will you do this? Different therapies
जाएंगे। ये कैसे करेंगे? अलग-अलग थेरेपीस
It will be. There will be different procedures. A Focus
होगी। अलग-अलग प्रोसीजर्स होंगे। एक फोकस
area is the length of the telomeres which are shortened
एरिया है टिलोमियर्स का लेंथ जो शॉर्टन
It happens. The DNA that is in our body
होता है। अ हमारे जो बॉडी में डीएनए है वो
in our body in the form of chromosomes
क्रोमोजोम्स के फॉर्म में हमारे बॉडी में
It is inside our cells. And if you are a
हमारे सेल्स के अंदर है वो। और अगर आप एक
If you look at a chromosome, its two ends
क्रोमोसोम देखेंगे तो उसके जो दो एंड्स
The parts of the end are called tillobears
हैं एंड के जो हिस्से हैं उसको टिलोबियर्स
They say. and it is found that as a
कहते हैं। और यह पाया जाता है कि जैसे एक
As a person grows older, the telomeres
व्यक्ति की आयु बढ़ती है वो टिलोमियर्स का
The length gradually shortens. because of that
लेंथ धीरे-धीरे शॉर्टन होता है। उसके कारण
This causes aging in our body. So the man
से एजिंग होता है हमारे बॉडी में। तो आदमी
People will get wrinkles. The different sciences
लोगों के रिंकल्स आ जाएंगे। अलग-अलग साइंस
And these are the symptoms of aging. So if you have
एंड सिम्टम्स हैं एजिंग के। तो अगर आपने
which is the process of telomere shortening
जो टिलोमीयर का शॉर्टेनिंग का प्रोसेस है
If you stop it, your ageing will also stop
उसको स्टॉप कर दिया तो आपका एजिंग भी बंद
Will be done. And if you look at Tilomors
हो जाएगा। और अगर आप टिलोमर्स को
If you can theoretically take it back then you
थ्योरेटिकली वापस लेंगन कर सकते हो तो यू
It is believed that it can actually reverse aging
कैन एक्चुअली रिवर्स एजिंग ऐसा माना जाता
Is. So this is one of the focus areas. And
है। तो दिस इज़ वन ऑफ़ द फोकस एरियाज़। और
If there is some progress in that then maybe we
उसमें कुछ प्रोग्रेस हुआ तो हम शायद
We will see that we can reverse aging
देखेंगे कि एजिंग को रिवर्स कर सकते हैं
Or you can at least stop it.
या फिर एटलीस्ट स्टॉप कर सकते हैं।
Basically actively in different domains
बेसिकली एक्टिवली अलग-अलग डोमेनस में
Research is ongoing. Crisper is one of them.
रिसर्च चल रहा है। क्रिसपर इज़ वन ऑफ़ देम।
Organ printing is another. all these domains
ऑर्गन प्रिंटिंग इज अनदर। ये सारे डोमेनस
By 2035. That means after 10 years, getting combined
2035 तक। यानी कि 10 साल बाद कंबाइन होकर
Yes everything it will add to longevity. But
हां सब कुछ इट विल ऐड टू लंजेविटी। पर
First and foremost longevity as a
फर्स्ट एंड फॉरमोस्ट लोंजेविटी एज अ
The service will be available for rich people.
सर्विस अवेलेबल होगा अमीर लोगों के लिए।
Naturally everyone is interested in technology
नेचुरली हर कोई टेक्नोलॉजी शुरुआत में
It is very expensive. Then slowly he
बहुत महंगी होती है। फिर धीरे-धीरे वो
There are parades everywhere. Ok. Moving on. Moving
परेड है हर जगह। ओके। मूविंग ऑन। मूविंग
On. A What's Next? 2040 neural
ऑन। अ नेक्स्ट क्या है? 2040 न्यूरल
Interfaces Allow Thought Based Computing. V
इंटरफेसिस अलाउ थॉट बेस्ड कंप्यूटिंग। वी
Should talk about Neuralink. Ah Second Brain
शुड टॉक अबाउट न्यूरालिंक। अह सेकंड ब्रेन
Implants restore lost memories. These
इंप्लांट्स रिस्टोर लॉस्ट मेमोरीज। ये
Both things are associated with Neuralink
दोनों चीज़े न्यूरालिंक से ही एसोसिएटेड
Is. Possibly possibly. Definitely
है। पॉसिब्ली पॉसिबबली। डेफिनेटली
There is an intersection of both technologies. these 15
इंटरसेक्शन है दोनों टेक्नोलॉजी का। ये 15
It is a year later. They are talking about 2040
साल बाद की बात है। ये 2040 की बात कर रहे
Are. Right? Neural Interface Allow Thought Based
हैं। राइट? न्यूरल इंटरफेस अलाउ थॉट बेस्ड
Computing. What could this mean?
कंप्यूटिंग। इसका मतलब क्या हो सकता है?
What is a neural interface? This is probably a
न्यूरल इंटरफेस क्या होता है? यह शायद एक
This is a chip that we will put inside our brain
चिप है जो हम अपने ब्रेन के अंदर डालेंगे
Which will be connected with the outside world.
जो बाहर की दुनिया के साथ कनेक्टेड होगा।
May be WiFi, Bluetooth whatever
मे बी वाईफाई, ब्लूटूथ व्हाटएवर कोई
whatever technology then this directly
व्हाटएवर टेक्नोलॉजी तो ये डायरेक्टली
physically some electrodes got damaged or
फिजिकली कुछ इलेक्ट्रोड्स हो गए या
Probes have been done which are of our brain
प्रोब्स हो गए जो हमारे ब्रेन का जो
there is a tissue, I will go inside and I will
टिश्यू है उसके अंदर जाएंगे एंड दे विल
connect the brain to an external device and
कनेक्ट द ब्रेन टू एन एक्सटर्नल डिवाइस और
multiple devices and we use our thoughts to access them
मल्टीपल डिवाइसेस और हम अपने थॉट से उन
make the devices communicate with
डिवाइसेस को के साथ कम्युनिक कर
Will be able to communicate. control them
कम्युनिकेट कर पाएंगे। उनको कंट्रोल कर
Will find it. So what happens today? if we
पाएंगे। तो आज क्या होता है? अगर हमें
If we want to write a program then we have to type
प्रोग्राम लिखना है तो हमें टाइप करना
it falls on a keyboard or from you
पड़ता है ऑन अ कीबोर्ड या फिर आपके से
on your phone or you can give voice
आपके फोन के ऊपर या फिर यू कैन गिव वॉइस
Commands to chat gpt. Right now you thought
कमांड्स टू चैट जीपीटी। अभी आप थॉट
You will be able to give commands. You don't even have to say
कमांड्स दे पाओगे। आपको बोलना भी नहीं
It will have to be done. so you can communicate with a
पड़ेगा। तो आप यू कैन कम्युनिकेट विथ अ
Computer. you can control a computer and
कंप्यूटर। यू कैन कंट्रोल अ कंप्यूटर और
Multiple Devices Just By Thought. it's like
मल्टीपल डिवाइसेस जस्ट बाय थॉट। इट्स लाइक
Telepathy. Hmm. So, It's Almost Magical
टेलीपैथी। हम्। तो, यह ऑलमोस्ट मैजिकल
Like this is the situation. but, or it could be
लाइक अह सिचुएशन है। लेकिन, या यह हो सकता
Is. Definitely, soon. ah second is also
है। डेफिनेटली, सून। अह सेकंड इज़ ऑल्सो
Link to this same topic. It is written that the brain
लिंक टू दिस सेम टॉपिक। लिखा है कि ब्रेन
Implants restore lost memories. I am
इंप्लांट्स रिस्टोर लॉस्ट मेमोरीज। आई एम
Skeptical about this. See Lost Memory
स्केप्टिकल अबाउट दिस। देखिए लॉस्ट मेमोरी
what happens is that something happens in your brain
क्या होता है कि आपके ब्रेन में कुछ
The information was solid but now it has disappeared
इंफॉर्मेशन स्टर्ड था वो अब वो गायब हो
Has gone. So there are two cases in this. either that
गया है। सो दो केसेस हैं इसमें। या तो वो
The information is still vague, but you can
इनफार्मेशन अभी भी स्टर्ड है लेकिन आप
You are not able to access it. because of
उसको एक्सेस नहीं कर पा रहे हो। बिकॉज़ ऑफ़
Whatever reason. if this is the situation
व्हाटएवर रीज़न। अगर ये सिचुएशन है तो
You may be able to access brain implants
ब्रेन इंप्लांट से यू मे बी एबल टू एक्सेस
That. But if that memory is overwritten
दैट। लेकिन अगर वो मेमोरी ओवराइट हो गई है
with a new memory or that memory
विथ अ न्यू मेमोरी या फिर वो मेमोरी
it is completely gone, it has been deleted so you
बिल्कुल चली ही गई डिलीट हो गई है तो आप
You will not be able to restore it. so it this is
उसको रिस्टोर नहीं कर पाओगे। सो इट दिस इज
Conditional this will depend. Ok
कंडीशनल दिस विल डिपेंड। ओके
Chat GBT has a small question. Let go
चैट जीबीटी को थोड़ा कुछ पूछना है। चलिए
I ask. Chat a little with GBT
पूछते हैं। चैट जीबीटी से थोड़ा सा बात कर
Let's take it. ok chat gbpt please answer in
लेते हैं। ओके चैट जीबपीटी प्लीज आंसर इन
Hindi. A what Elon Musk is doing with Neura
हिंदी। अ जो ईलॉन मस्क कर रहे हैं न्यूरा
A Vo in 5 Sentences with Link
लिंक के साथ अ वो पांच सेंटेंसेस में
Please explain. Suppose a five year old child
समझाइए। मान लो कि एक पांच साल का बच्चा
If someone is listening to you then these are very easy ways
आपकी बातें सुन रहा है तो एकदम आसान तरीके
Please explain it to me. and the second thing tell me this
से समझाइए प्लीज। एंड सेकंड चीज यह बताइए
that what you printed in the 2040 column
कि जो आपने 2040 के कॉलम में प्रिंट किया
that neural interfaces allow thought based
है कि न्यूरल इंटरफेससेस अलाउ थॉट बेस्ड
Computing. From that perspective, tell me that
कंप्यूटिंग। अ उस नजरिए से यह बताइए कि
Social media
सोशल मीडिया
What will be the evolution in? means we are social
में एववोल्यूशन क्या होगा? मतलब हम सोशल
How will you use the media? these three four
मीडिया को यूज़ कैसे करेंगे? ये तीनचार
Tell me in sentences.
सेंटेंस में बताइए।
Absolutely. So Neuralink's work is our
बिल्कुल। तो न्यूरालिंक का काम है हमारे
Putting a small chip in the brain so that we can
दिमाग में एक छोटा सा चिप लगाना जिससे हम
Can talk directly to the computer or machine.
सीधे कंप्यूटर या मशीन से बात कर सकें।
Like music without touching hands, just by thinking
जैसे बिना हाथ लगाए सिर्फ सोचकर म्यूजिक
Listen or watch a video. It is for those
सुनना या वीडियो देखना। यह उन लोगों के
It can also be helpful for those who are unable to walk
लिए भी मददगार हो सकता है जो चल फिर नहीं
Can. Now till 2040 when thought based computing
सकते। अब 2040 तक जब थॉट बेस्ड कंप्यूटिंग
If it comes, think how social media will change.
आएगी तो सोचिए सोशल मीडिया कैसे बदलेगा।
Just think about it and post your post.
आप बस सोचेंगे और अपना पोस्ट कर देंगे
without typing or on someone's post
बिना टाइप किए या किसी के पोस्ट पर
You will be able to react just by thinking. From this
रिएक्शन भी सिर्फ सोच कर दे पाएंगे। इससे
social media will become more personal but
सोशल मीडिया और पर्सनल हो जाएगा लेकिन
New challenges of privacy will also emerge. it
प्राइवेसी के नए चैलेंजेस भी आएंगे। यह
The future is very exciting and we
भविष्य काफी रोमांचक है और हमें इन
You will have to keep yourself prepared for the changes.
बदलावों के लिए खुद को तैयार रखना होगा।
I have a friend named Saket Modi. that one
मेरे एक फ्रेंड है साकेत मोदी। वो एक
Is a cyber security expert. They
साइबर सिक्योरिटी एक्सपर्ट है। उन्होंने
Basically it is said that in the coming 5, 10, 15 years
बेसिकली ये कहा कि आने वाले 5 10 15 सालों
in almost everyone
में ऑलमोस्ट हर
A small utility oriented device inside
यूटिलिटी ओरिएंटेड डिवाइस के अंदर एक छोटा
There will be some computer. The chip will remain. And
सा कंप्यूटर तो रहेगा। चिप तो रहेगा। और
If that chip is present then that chip is hacked
अगर वो चिप प्रेजेंट है तो वो चिप्स हैक
can also be. It can definitely happen. So
भी हो सकते हैं। बिल्कुल हो सकता है। तो
Suppose if everyone had neuraling installed
मान लो अगर हर किसी ने न्यूरालिंग डाला
Think about it in your skull. Yes. And someone else
अपने स्कल में सोचिए। हां। और किसी
The terrorist group realized that good
टेररिस्ट ग्रुप ने यह जान लिया कि अच्छा
How to hack. So neither does that chips hack
हैक कैसे करते हैं। तो ना ही वह चिप्स हैक
Yes, but that whole person will get hacked. Less
होंगे पर वो पूरा इंसान हैक हो जाएगा। कम
It can retrieve all your memories in less than
से कम आपकी सारी मेमोरीज को वो रिट्रीव कर
Will find it. whatever you think whatever you think
पाएंगे। आप जो भी कुछ सोचते हैं सो जो कुछ
We also know that it will not remain private.
भी जानते हैं वो प्राइवेट नहीं रहेगा।
Imagine that your inner most thoughts are
इमेजिन दैट आपकी जो इनर मोस्ट थॉट्स है वो
Maybe he will know. It's possible. Hmm.
शायद जान पाएंगे वो। इट्स पॉसिबल। हम्म।
what would you like to say based on this
आप क्या कहना चाहोगे बेस्ड ऑन दिस
Conversations with GPT are progressing well
कॉन्वर्सेशन विथ जीपीटी एज वेल एज
Everything we have spoken about. What to say
एवरीथिंग वी हैव स्पोकन अबाउट। क्या कहना
would you like it? I think technology is very fast
चाहोगे? आई थिंक टेक्नोलॉजी बहुत फास्ट
Progress is being made. specially in the
प्रोग्रेस हो रही है। एस्पेशली इन द इन द
Field of AI. and its so fast
फील्ड ऑफ एआई। और उसके इतना फास्ट
Progress is being made that we are not we may
प्रोग्रेस हो रही है कि वी आर नॉट वी मे
Not be aware of the risks of all the risks.
नॉट बी अवेयर ऑफ द रिस्क्स ऑफ ऑल द रिस्क।
And even if we are aware, then it is so soon
और अगर हम अवेयर भी हैं तो इतना जल्दी
Progress is happening that we may not be able to
प्रोग्रेस हो रहा है कि वी मे नॉट बी एबल
To mitigate all the risks. so like you said
टू मिटिगेट ऑल द रिस्क। तो जैसे आपने कहा
that if someone implants Neuralink
कि अगर किसी ने न्यूरालिंक का इंप्लांट
but adequate security measures
लिया है लेकिन एडिक्वेट सिक्योरिटी मेजर्स
It might not be possible. in that case somebody
पॉसिबल शायद नहीं होंगे। इन दैट केस समबडी
Able to Steal Your Memories. Hmm. and maybe
एबल टू स्टील योर मेमोरीज। हम्। और मेबी
God.
देव।
So there are many possibilities. and its
तो बहुत सारे पॉसिबिलिटीज़ हैं। और इसका
Look at this we definitely think I will
इसका हमें डेफिनेटली आई थिंक देखिए
the scientists and the engineers
साइंटिस्ट्स और और इंजीनियर्स तो
We will create the technology. But this ethical
टेक्नोलॉजी बनाएंगे। लेकिन ये जो एथिकल
There are concerns, there is ethical risk, mitigate it
कंसर्न्स है, एथिकल रिस्क है उसको मिटिगेट
We may need to use legislation to do this
करने के लिए हमें लेजिसलेशन का शायद यूज़
Have to do it. that will give the tension to politicians
करना पड़े। दैट विल गिव द टशन टू पॉलिटिशंस
to legislate things over and try to
टू ओवर लेजिसलेट थिंग्स एंड ट्राई टू
Control everything. so these are the challenges
कंट्रोल एवरीथिंग। तो दीज़ आर द चैलेंजज़
Coming up. These. These. These. These. These. These. These.
कमिंग अप। ये। ये। ये। ये। ये। ये। ये।
These. These. These. We have to face all these challenges
ये। ये। ये। ये सब चैलेंजज़ हमें फेस करने
Will be. Hmm. And we are already there today
होंगे। हम्म। और आज ऑलरेडी हम वहां पहुंच
have been done. Sir I watch more TV shows and movies
चुके हैं। सर मैं ज्यादा टीवी शोज़ फिल्में
I don't watch it these days. An out and out at 4:00
आजकल नहीं देखता हूं। पर एक आउट एंड आउट
Recommendation for all viewers. If
रेकमेंडेशन है सारे व्यूअर्स के लिए। अगर
Those people liked this conversation
उन सों को ये वाली कन्वर्सेशन अच्छी लग
It has been happening. So please don't go to Netflix
रही है। तो प्लीज जाकर ना Netflix पर
Watch Black Mirror. a lot of who
ब्लैक मिरर देखिए। बहुत सारे जो
All the Black Mirrors around the world are futurists
फ्यूचरिस्ट हैं दुनिया भर सारे ब्लैक मिरर
praises him a lot because he says
की बहुत तारीफें करते हैं क्योंकि वो कहते
that this is a very accurate description of the
हैं कि ये एक बहुत एक्यूरेट डिप्शन ऑफ़ द
There is a future. There is a slight negative outlook
फ्यूचर है। थोड़ी सी एक नेगेटिव आउटलुक है
Regarding the future. and the black mirror is mystic
फ्यूचर को लेकर। और ब्लैक मिरर मिस्टिक है
What? Yes. That means it says that like
क्या? हां। मतलब ये ये कहते हैं कि जैसे
Suppose we talked about Neuralink, then one
मान लो हमने न्यूरालिंक की बात करी तो एक
Neuralink as an Actual Full Episode
पूरे एपिसोड में न्यूरालिंक एज एन एक्चुअल
Technology is shown. then the scary ones
टेक्नोलॉजी दिखाई गई है। फिर जो डरावने
The outcomes are that for example, suppose if
आउटकम्स हैं कि फॉर एग्जांपल मान लो अगर
If someone commits a crime then what then 2025
किसी ने क्राइम कमिट करी तो क्या तो 2025
If someone commits a crime in
में अगर कोई क्राइम कमिट करता है तो
He is sent to jail.
उन्हें जेल भेजा जाता है।
Brain chips with Neura Link in 2040
2040 में न्यूरा लिंक के साथ ब्रेन चिप्स
If someone commits a crime because of
की वजह से अगर किसी ने क्राइम कमिट करी तो
They can change it by manipulating their chip
उनके चिप को मैनपुलेट करके दे कैन चेंज दे
Perception of time. Good. That means their
परसेप्शन ऑफ़ टाइम। अच्छा। यानी कि उनके
The brain will feel like it has spent 20 years
दिमाग को ऐसा लगेगा कि उन्होंने 20 साल
spent in jail but actually in real life
जेल में बिताया बट एक्चुअली रियल लाइफ में
he's just spent a day thru a
उन्होंने सिर्फ एक दिन बिताया है थ्रू अ
Software. Good. Good. or all of these
सॉफ्टवेयर। अच्छा। अच्छा। या ये सब
Possibility may come. Yes. Yes. so such
पॉसिबिलिटी आ सकती है। यस। हां। तो ऐसे
Thought Experiments Are Shown in Black
थॉट एक्सपेरिमेंट्स दिखाए गए हैं ब्लैक
In the mirror. Good. Good. very very
मिरर में। अच्छा। अच्छा। वेरी वेरी
Interesting. Ah and highly recommended.
इंटरेस्टिंग। अह एंड हाइली रेकमेंडेड।
meaning it's probably the one show that affected
मतलब इट्स प्रॉबब्ली द वन शो दैट अफेक्टेड
my creativity the most as a media
माय क्रिएटिविटी द मोस्ट एज अ मीडिया
Professional. ok ok. Interesting. End
प्रोफेशनल। अच्छा अच्छा। इंटरेस्टिंग। एंड
It fuels this episode as well. Ok.
इट्स फ्यूल दिस एपिसोड एज वेल। ओके।
Moving on. Yes. Ok. Umm
मूविंग ऑन। यस। ओके। अम्म
2045.
2045.
Synthetic Biology Enables Designers
सिंथेटिक बायोलॉजी इनेबल्स डिजाइनर
Organisms.
ऑर्गेनिज्म्स।
If you have a dog who wants to have wings
आपको अगर एक डॉग है जिसको जिसको आपको पंख
If you want to give wings, you can probably do that.
पंख देना है, तो आप शायद वह कर पाओगे।
that's not that thing you know crazy stuff okay or
दैट्स नॉट थिंग यू नो क्रेजी स्टफ ओके या
I mean I don’t feel like expanding that
आई मीन आई डोंट फील लाइक एक्सपेंडिंग दैट
Right
राइट
Moving On To 2050 AI Generated Art Rivals
मूविंग ऑन 2050 एआई जनरेटेड आर्ट राइवल्स
Human Creativity
ह्यूमन क्रिएटिविटी
it's basically saying that content creators
इट्स बेसिकली सेइंग कि कंटेंट क्रिएटर्स
there will be no jobs left for
के पास जॉब्स नहीं बचेंग नहीं बचेंगी
jobs yes artists painters whatever
जॉब्स यस आर्टिस्ट पेंटर्स व्हाटएवर
Musicians who are currently graphic novelists
म्यूजिशियंस जो अभी अभी लोग ग्राफिक
Ghibli says about the designers
डिजाइनर्स के बारे में कह रहे हैं गिबली
Everyone is doing it because of the generated images
जनरेटेड इमेजेस की वजह से हर कोई कर रहा
yes but he is eventually content
है अभी वो यस बट वो इवेंचुअली कंटेंट
Yes, May Be You will be true for creators too
क्रिएटर्स के लिए भी सच होगा हां मे बी यू
Will Have AI Design AI Generated Podcast
विल हैव एआई डिजाइन एआई जनरेटेड पॉडकास्ट
what not who knows music you know high
व्हाट नॉट हु नोस म्यूजिक यू नो हाई
Quality Music AI Generated Films A
क्वालिटी म्यूजिक ए आई जनरेटेड फिल्म्स ए
I generated films which will be even better
आई जनरेटेड फिल्म्स व्हिच विल बी इवन बेटर
Than Human Human Generated Films Possible
देन ह्यूमन ह्यूमन जनरेटेड फिल्म्स पॉसिबल
is it or i am pretty sure in 20 50
है या आई एम प्रीटी श्योर 20 50 में
there will be such software that you can just
ऐसे सॉफ्टवेयर होंगे कि आप बस सॉफ्टवेयर
tell me that I want to see a movie which
में कह दो कि मुझे एक मूवी देखनी है जिसकी
The theme will be horror and Shahrukh will be the hero
थीम होगी हॉरर जिसके हीरो होंगे शाहरुख
whose heroine will be Juhi Chawla and please one
जिसकी हीरोइन होगी जूही चावला और प्लीज एक
make a movie just that software will be to
मूवी बना दो बस दैट सॉफ्टवेयर विल बी टू
make the movie i'm sure it happens which is very
मेक द मूवी आई श्योर इट हैपन जो बहुत
It will be interesting, it will also be interesting, yes
इंटरेस्टिंग रहेगी इंटरेस्टिंग भी होगी यस
And according to my test you should have
और मेरे टेस्ट के अनुसार होनी चाहिए आपको
He will also know your taste, we are so content
वो आपका टेस्ट भी जानेगा हम हम सो कंटेंट
For creators For TV show runners
क्रिएटर्स के लिए टीवी शो रनर्स के लिए
This is the finale for the film people
फिल्म के लोगों के लिए दिस इज़ द फाइनल
Years 20-50 is the deadline means another 25 years
इयर्स 20-50 इज द डेडलाइन मतलब और 25 साल
There are some left. hmm ah and the second one bio
बचे हैं। हम्म अह एंड द सेकंड वन बायो
Implants become standard for health
इंप्लांट्स बिकम स्टैंडर्ड फॉर हेल्थ
Optimization. means i am not sure that
ऑप्टिमाइजेशन। मतलब आई एम नॉट श्योर वो
What does Bio Implants want to say? A
क्या कहना चाहता है बायो इंप्लांट्स? अ
sounds like a very dark scenario that her
साउंड्स लाइक अ वेरी डार्क सिनेरियो कि हर
Someone will have a biological implant
किसी के पास एक बायोलॉजिकल इंप्लांट होगा
So that the government can see what you are doing
जिससे गवर्नमेंट देखेगी कि आप आपके क्या
There is a paraphernalia and it will be able to
पैराटर्स है और इट विल बी एबल टू
Predict's brother will have heart attack in six months
प्रेडिक्ट के भाई इनको छ महीने में हार्ट
If an attack is about to happen then you can take the
अटैक आने वाला है तो यू कैन टेक द
Preventive measures and all that may happen
प्रिवेंटिव मेजर्स एंड ऑल दैट शायद ऐसा
They are saying something, meaning inside the body
कुछ बोल रहे हैं वो मतलब बॉडी के अंदर
aadhar card perhaps something like that to that
आधार कार्ड परहैप्स समथिंग लाइक दैट तो वो
will know everything and that predictive analysis
सब कुछ जानेगा और वो प्रेडिक्टिव एनालिसिस
will be able to do that in six months this can be a
कर पाएगा कि छ महीने में ये हो सकता है एक
This could happen to you within a year
साल के अंदर ये हो सकता है आपको
Osteoporosis will occur between 20 and 35 years
ऑस्टियोपोरोसिस 20 35 इयर्स तक हो जाएगा
So you do this. so, this will
तो आप आप यह कर लीजिए। सो, दिस विल
Essentially Extend Your Life Span and
एसेंशियली एक्सटेंड योर लाइफ स्पैन एंड
Quality of life. That's a dangerous thing.
क्वालिटी ऑफ़ लाइफ। दैट्स अ डेंजरस थिंग।
We don't want that much control. they be a loss
वी डोंट वांट दैट मच कंट्रोल। दे बी अ लॉस
of privacy. Yes. Ok. anything else you
ऑफ़ प्राइवेसी। हां। ओके। एनीथिंग एल्स यू
Want to talk about that? right now at this point
वांट टू टॉक अबाउट दैट? अभी इस पॉइंट के
bad i think we can move fast because here
बाद आई थिंक वी कैन मूव फ़ास्ट बिकॉज़ यहां
No, I don't think that GPT has also made any mistakes.
ना मुझे लग रहा है कि जीपीटी ने भी तुक्के
Have planted it. Yes. the further you go the more
लगाए हैं। हां। द फर्दर यू गो द मोर
Speculative it became. Speculative. Yes.
स्पेकुलेटिव इट बिकम। स्पेकुलेटिव। यस।
Speculation. A ok. 2060 AI Companions
स्पेकुलेशन। अ ओके। 2060 एआई कंपैनियंस
Pass the Turing test for emotional bonding.
पास ट्यूरिंग टेस्ट फॉर इमोशनल बॉन्डिंग।
What is Turing test sir? Turing
ट्यूरिंग टेस्ट क्या होता है सर? ट्यूरिंग
The test is if you have a
टेस्ट ये होता है कि अगर आपके पास एक
There is something on the other side of the screen. His
स्क्रीन है उसके उस तरफ कुछ तो है। उसके
if you communicate with and if you
साथ अगर आप कम्युनिकेट करते हो और अगर आप
You won't be able to tell if there's a robot on your side or not
कह नहीं पाओगे कि आपके उस तरफ रोबोट है या
Human is more than that thing on the other side
ह्यूमन है देन दैट दैट थिंग ऑन द अदर साइड
It has passed the Turing test. because it is
इट हज़ पास द ट्यूरिंग टेस्ट। बिकॉज़ इट इज़
able to convince you that that is the
एबल टू कन्विन्स यू दैट दैट दैट दैट दैट
That's what is human. So this Turing test
दैट दैट इज़ ह्यूमन। तो ये ट्यूरिंग टेस्ट
Done. I think GBT did it
हो गया। मुझे तो लगता है जीबीटी ने हो गया
Yes. Done. No? It's become official.
जी। हो गया। ना? इट्स बिकम ऑफिशियल।
Almost late. So what is written here? AI
ऑलमोस्ट देर। तो ये क्या लिखा है? एआई
Companions pass the Turing test for emotions
कंपैनियंस पास ट्यूरिंग टेस्ट फॉर इमोशनल
Bonding. well it's during this for
बॉन्डिंग। अच्छा इट्स ड्यूरिंग दिस फॉर
emotional bonding emotional bonding it will
इमोशनल बॉन्डिंग इमोशनल बॉन्डिंग इट विल
have emotions just like humans if you
हैव इमोशंस जस्ट लाइक ह्यूमंस अगर आपके
You have a robot companion
पास एक रोबोट कंपैनियन है आप आपको कोई
If you could not find a wife for example then you found one
पत्नी नहीं मिली फॉर एग्जांपल तो आपने एक
I adopted a robot, I mean I bought it, then that
रोबोट पाल लिया आई मीन खरीद लिया देन दैट
The robot will be able to emote just like a
रोबोट विल बी एबल टू इमोट जस्ट लाइक अ
human being hmm wow okay so basically this
ह्यूमन बीइंग हम्म वाह ओके सो बेसिकली ये
There is a prediction for 2060, yes, that means what
2060 के लिए प्रेडिक्शन है यस यानी क्या
35 years left 35 years from today ok to right
35 इयर्स लेफ्ट आज से 35 साल ओके तो राइट
Now I believe GPT passed the Turing test
नाउ आई बिलीव जीपीटी ने वो ट्यूरिंग टेस्ट
passed it can behave like a human
पास कर दिया इट कैन बिहेव लाइक अ ह्यूमन
being but they are saying that from an
बीइंग बट ये कह कह रहे हैं कि फ्रॉम एन
A little bit of emotional perspective
इमोशनल पर्सपेक्टिव ये थोड़ा सा
It is speculative. I think even now if you I
स्पेकुलेटिव है। आई थिंक इवन नाउ इफ यू आई
Think in two-three years it will be able to emote
थिंक दो-ती साल में इट विल बी एबल टू इमोट
Just like a human. we are okay and the other
जस्ट लाइक अ ह्यूमन। हम अ ओके एंड द अदर
Prediction Is Neural Augmentation Boost
प्रेडिक्शन इज़ न्यूरल ऑगमेंटेशन बूस्ट
intelligence bean that brain you put a chip in
इंटेलिजेंस सेम कि ब्रेन आपने एक चिप डाल
Gave. Your IQ should be between 120 and 125
दिया। आपका आईक्यू 120 से लेकर 125 हो
Went. It became 150. Now here's the timeline again
गया। 150 हो गया। अब ये टाइमलाइन फिर से
It becomes interesting in 2065. hmm
इंटरेस्टिंग बन जाती है 2065 में। हम्
Mind uploading in clinical testing
माइंड अपलोडिंग इन क्लीनिकल टेस्टिंग जी
This means that you have a computer
इसका मतलब यह है कि आपके पास एक कंप्यूटर
there is a system on which you can set up your
सिस्टम है जिसके ऊपर जिसके अंदर आप अपना
your mind your consciousness upload
दिमाग अपना माइंड अपना कॉन्शियसनेस अपलोड
if you can then it means copy paste sorry you 90
कर सकते हो तो मतलब कॉपी पेस्ट सॉरी आप 90
The years will be rough and wonderful, wood you do it
साल के होंगे रफली बढ़िया वुड यू डू इट
What benefit will it give me? Let's see
उससे मेरा मुझे क्या फायदा होगा देखिए एक
The advantage is that after my death
फायदा फायदा यह है कि मेरे मेरी मृत्यु के
My consciousness will remain alive even after
पश्चात भी मेरा कॉन्शियसनेस जीवित रहेगा
In as a copy of my current consciousness. So
इन एज अ कॉपी ऑफ़ माय करंट कॉन्शियसनेस। तो
If after 300 years someone thinks that
अगर 300 साल के बाद अगर कोई सोचेगा कि
I want to talk to Abhijeet Chawla
मुझे अभिजीत चावला से बात करना है उनकी
wisdom if that so called wisdom is tapped in
विज़डम अगर जो सो कॉल्ड विज़डम को टैप इन
If you want to do it then there will be a copy for reference.
करना है तो वो एक कॉपी रहेगी फॉर रेफरेंस।
We hope this will be a service to the society
हम ये समाज के लिए शायद होपफुली सेवा होगी
To have my consciousness there. But think about it
टू हैव माय कॉन्शियसनेस देयर। लेकिन सोचिए
if you are a genuine consciousness
अगर आप एक कॉन्शियसनेस हो जेन्युइन
Consciousness and you are locked in a box
कॉन्शियसनेस और आप एक डब्बे के अंदर बंद
Ho won't it be torture for you? we are this
हो विल इट नॉट बी टॉर्चर फॉर यू? हम तो ये
there is ethical concern and the other thing is that you
एथिकल कंसर्न है और दूसरी बात ये है कि आप
if you upload consciousness into a
अगर कॉन्शसनेस को अपलोड करते हो इंटू अ
Computers and a System It Doesn't Mean You Are
कंप्यूटर और अ सिस्टम इट डजंट मीन यू आर
Immortal. you will die and your consciousness will disappear
इमोर्टल। यू विल डाई एंड योर कॉन्शसनेस जो
She is original conscious, she will go. assume that means
ओरिजिनल कॉन्शस है वो जाएगी। मतलब मान लो
That there is consciousness within you. They
कि आपके अंदर ही अंदर कॉन्शियसनेस है। वो
then normal human life will be lived and human
तो नॉर्मल ह्यूमन लाइफ जिएगा और ह्यूमन
Death will die. Absolutely. But you are conscious of that
डेथ मरेगा। बिल्कुल। बट आप उसी कॉन्शियस
xerox it and put it in the computer
को ज़ेरॉक्स करके कंप्यूटर में डाल हां
you will have a copy but you
आपके पास एक कॉपी हो जाएगी लेकिन आप तो
will surely die like in the star truck
मरेंगे ही मरेंगे जैसे स्टार ट्रक में
Let's show the captain that he goes from here to there
दिखाते हैं कैप्टन का कि यहां से वहां चले
If you go then whatever body is here,
गए तो ये यहां पे जो जो बॉडी है उनका वो
is destroyed and a copy is created there
नष्ट होता है और एक कॉपी वहां उत्पन्न
if it happens then it is not the same person it's a
होता है तो इट इज़ नॉट द सेम पर्सन इट्स अ
copy hum hum for perspective
कॉपी हम हम फॉर पर्सेक्टिव
Shahrukh Salman Aamir will be 100 years old in 2065
2065 में शाहरुख सलमान आमिर 100 साल के
honge kya baat hai it will be the 100th birthday
होंगे क्या बात है इट विल बी द 100 बर्थडे
This is how it means that mind uploading will happen
ऐसे तो डस इट मीन कि माइंड अपलोडिंग विल
Lead to a copy of Shahrukh, Salman and Aamir
लीड टू अ कॉपी ऑफ़ शाहरुख, सलमान एंड आमिर
in your phone also. Yes, it is possible.
इन योर फोन आल्सो। यस, इट इज़ पॉसिबल।
Definitely. if they are still alive and they
डेफिनेटली। इफ दे आर स्टिल अलाइव एंड दे
Can upload their minds. you may be able to
कैन अपलोड देर माइंड्स। यू मे बी एबल टू
Purchase a copy. Good. Ask him. Ok.
परचेस अ कॉपी। अच्छा। पूछें इसको। ओके।
GBT, this is what you wrote about 2065
जीबीटी, यह जो आपने लिखा है 2065 के बारे
In, Mind Uploading in Clinical
में, माइंड अपलोडिंग इन क्लीनिकल
"Tests." What do you mean? Actually
टेस्ट्स।" आपका मतलब क्या है? एक्चुअली
Many Black Mirror episodes are based on this theme
काफी सारे ब्लैक मिरर एपिसोड्स इस थीम पे
Are based. but you tell me what do you
बेस्ड हैं। पर आप बताइए कि व्हाट डू यू
What do you mean by mind uploading? friend and this mind
मीन बाय माइंड अपलोडिंग? यार और इस माइंड
Due to uploading, the life of common people is affected
अपलोडिंग की वजह से आम जनता की जिंदगी
How will it change? Ok. of mind uploading
कैसे बदलेगी? ठीक है। माइंड अपलोडिंग का
It means complete awareness or consciousness of the mind.
मतलब है दिमाग की पूरी जानकारी या चेतना
Save it in digital form. As
को डिजिटल रूप में सेव करना। जैसे
Just like you save a file on your computer
कंप्यूटर में फाइल सेव करते हैं वैसे ही
your brain's memories, preferences,
अपने दिमाग की यादें, प्रेफरेंसेस,
Personality and thought in the digital world
व्यक्तित्व और सोच को डिजिटल दुनिया में
To upload. Now this clinical test will be done till 2065
अपलोड करना। अब 2065 तक यह क्लीनिकल टेस्ट
I can come in. This makes the lives of common people
में आ सकता है। इससे आम लोगों की जिंदगी
Revolutionary changes may occur. As
में क्रांतिकारी बदलाव हो सकते हैं। जैसे
Digitally connect with loved ones even after death
जीवन के बाद भी अपनों के साथ डिजिटल रूप
being present in the new digital world
में मौजूद रहना या नई डिजिटल दुनिया में
Exploring yourself.
खुद को एक्सप्लोर करना।
New meaning to yourself in the new digital world
नई मतलब नई डिजिटल दुनिया में खुद को
Exploring means exploring the digital world
एक्सप्लोर करना मतलब मतलब डिजिटल दुनिया
You can live your consciousness in new forms
में आप अपनी चेतना को नए रूपों में जी
Can be done. like in virtual reality
सकते हैं। जैसे वर्चुअल रियलिटी में
Live in different avatars, explore new places
अलग-अलग अवतार में रहना, नई जगह एक्सप्लोर
or with loved ones in virtual space
करना या अपनों के साथ वर्चुअल स्पेस में
communicate. All this is in digital form
बातचीत करना। ये सब कुछ डिजिटल रूप में
will be. Ok. I disagree with that. it is a
होगा। ओके। आई डिसएग्री विथ दैट। इट इज अ
Copy of you. You are not doing all this.
कॉपी ऑफ यू। आप नहीं कर रहे हो ये सब।
There is a copy of you that is doing all this. My
आपका एक कॉपी है जो ये सब कर रहा है। मेरे
Think about this for your grandchildren
ख्याल से ये ना आपके पोते पोती के लिए
Yes, it will be beneficial if my grandfather is still alive
फायदेमंद होगा हां कि यार दादाजी रह गए
With us. yes but for you
हमारे साथ। हां लेकिन आपके लिए वो
It will not be beneficial. hmm so this kind of
फायदेमंद नहीं होगा। हम्म तो इस प्रकार का
This will be a revolutionary thing but AI is
रिवोल्यूशनरी चीज होगी ये लेकिन एआई इज
not able to differentiate between two
नॉट एबल टू डिफरेंशिएट बिटवीन टू
Consciousness. He is thinking that your
कॉन्शियसनेसेस। वो सोच रहा है कि आपका जो
It is a copy and that too is you. You are not. I
कॉपी है वो भी आप ही हो। आप नहीं हो। आई
I think we don't even talk about cloning
आई थिंक हमें ना क्लोनिंग की बातें भी
Should be done. And here is actually the cloning
करनी चाहिए। और यहां एक्चुअली क्लोनिंग के
Nothing was written about it.
बारे में कुछ भी नहीं लिखा गया।
Interesting. Hey, tell me how far cloning has gone
इंटरेस्टिंग। अ आप बताइए क्लोनिंग कहां तक
Has it arrived? Because I know pet cloning
पहुंचा है? क्योंकि एक आई नो पेट क्लोनिंग
Is becoming a dream for a lot of you. People
इज बिकमिंग अ ड्रीम फॉर अ लॉट ऑफ़ यू। लोग
They say that my dog ​​loves me a lot
कहते हैं कि यार मेरे कुत्ते से मुझे बहुत
I have more attachment. so before the dog dies
ज्यादा लगाव है। तो कुत्ते के डेथ से पहले
I have stored some of his biological samples.
मैंने उसका कुछ बायोलॉजिकल सैंपल स्टोर कर
and when cloning becomes possible then I
दिया और जब क्लोनिंग पॉसिबल होगी तब मैं
bringing my dog ​​back to life
मेरे कुत्ते को फिर से जीवित करके उस
another dog's life with a dog another
कुत्ते के साथ एक और कुत्ते का जीवन एक और
I can spend one more innings.
एक और इनिंग्स बिता सकूं।
What is cloning? An organism is
क्लोनिंग क्या होता है कि एक ऑर्गेनिज्म
You can make an exact genetic copy of it.
का एग्जैक्ट जेनेटिक कॉपी आप बना सकते हो।
For example you have a Shanna,
फॉर एग्जांपल आपके पास एक शानना है,
There is a dog. You took one of his hairs.
कुत्ता है। उसका आपने एक बाल ले लिया।
He won't feel any pain by having his hair taken. That
उसको कुछ पीड़ा नहीं होगी बाल लेने से। उस
The hair has its genetic code inside it. Complete
बाल के अंदर उसका जेनेटिक कोड है। पूरा
The genome is inside it. Now you can call a technician
जीनोम है उसके अंदर। अब आप किसी टेक्नशियन
Give it to the genetic lab. he that
को दे दे दीजिए जेनेटिक लैब में। वो उस
will sequence the DNA and through genetic
डीएनए को सीक्वेंस करेगा और थ्रू जेनेटिक
technology that is already available today
टेक्नोलॉजी जो आज ऑलरेडी उपलब्ध है उसी का
Can make a replica. for example
एक रेप्लिका बना सकते हैं। फॉर एग्जांपल
A sheep was cloned some 2030 years ago
कुछ 2030 साल पहले एक शीप का क्लोनिंग हुआ
was dolly there the first ever cloning ever
था डॉली देयर द फर्स्ट एवर क्लोनिंग एवर
Done. Right now it's a lot of routine with rats and
डन। अभी तो काफी रूटीन है विथ रैट्स एंड
Small you know lower level organisms. So
स्मॉल यू नो लोअर लेवल ऑर्गेनिज्म्स। तो
Cloning a dog can happen easily. Cat's
डॉग का क्लोनिंग ईली हो सकता है। कैट का
It can be done easily. Technically human too
इजीली हो सकता है। टेक्निकली ह्यूमन का भी
Maybe but it is not ethically allowed.
हो सकता है बट एथिकली अलाउड नहीं है।
It is not legally allowed in most countries. So
लीगली अलाउड नहीं है इन मोस्ट कंट्रीज। तो
Definitely if your dog is dead
डेफिनेटली अगर आपका कुत्ता मर गया है तो
You have some of his genetic samples.
उसके उसका कुछ जेनेटिक सैंपल है आपके पास
So from that you can get a new one with the same genetic code
तो उससे आप उसी जेनेटिक कोड वाला नया
You can make a dog through the technology
कुत्ता बना सकते हो थ्रू द द टेक्नोलॉजी
but it is not the same organism, it's a
लेकिन इट इज़ नॉट द सेम ऑर्गेनिज्म इट्स अ
Different dog with the same genetics but here
डिफरेंट डॉग विथ द सेम जेनेटिक्स बट यहां
Also, we are talking about biology. I
भी ना हम बायोलॉजी की बात कर रहे हैं। आई
Think about the output given by GBT.
थिंक ये जो जीबीटी ने आउटपुट दिया है कि
mind uploading that is digital that is a
माइंड अपलोडिंग दैट इज डिजिटल दैट्स अ
digital technology yes big difference do you
डिजिटल टेक्नोलॉजी यस बिग डिफरेंस डू यू
Think human cloning will become a reality even today
थिंक ह्यूमन क्लोनिंग रियलिटी बनेगी आज भी
If the technology can be made then it is available
बन सकती है टेक्नोलॉजी तो अवेलेबल है
Is there exactly an ethical dilemma in this?
एक्जेक्टली इसमें एथिकल डलेमा है क्या
The ethical dilemma is what you are doing
एथिकल डलेमा ये है कि यू आर डूइंग व्हाट
God is suppose to do it if you have this
गॉड इज सपोज टू डू अगर आपके पास ये
I have the ability to take Ranveer's DNA
एबिलिटी है कि मैंने रणवीर का डीएनए ले
For example, I stole every single hair
लिया फॉर एग्जांपल एक एक बाल मैंने चोरी
your com is done fine with your brush
कर लिया आपके के कॉम आपके ब्रश से ठीक है
You didn't even know I took a hair
आपको पता भी नहीं चला एक बाल ले ली मैंने
I extracted your DNA from it
उससे मैंने आपका डीएनए एक्सट्रैक्ट किया
So I can make 15 new clones of Ranveer
तो मैं 15 रणवीर के नए क्लोन बना सकता हूं
and then I can I don't know with her
एंड देन आई कैन आई डोंट नो उसके उसके साथ
what will i do i have that evil mind
मैं क्या करूंगा मेरे पास वो इविल माइंड
no but i am sure there are lots of lots of
नहीं है लेकिन आई एम श्योर लॉट ऑफ लॉट ऑफ़
Evil Things You Can Do With That One Religious Person
इविल थिंग्स यू कैन डू विथ दैट एक धार्मिक
Bring perspective tell it to soul
पर्सपेक्टिव लाओ इसमें बताइए आत्मा सेम
will it be different or will it be different no 100% different
होगी कि अलग अलग होगी नो 100% अलग अलग अलग
soul will be there so you are playing god it is
आत्मा होगी सो यू आर प्लेइंग गॉड इट इज़
it's not a good thing right it means no
इट्स नॉट अ गुड थिंग राइट ये मतलब नो
human beings should have the ability and
ह्यूमन बीइंग शुड हैव द एबिलिटी और
Capacity to do this but this is all there is today
कैपेसिटी टू डू दिस बट आज तो यही ये सब है
Your body is same, your soul is different and theirs is also different
बॉडी सेम आत्मा अलग बॉडी भी आपकी अलग उनकी
It may be different depending on what diet
अलग हो सकती है डिपेंडिंग ऑन कि क्या डाइट
did they get the nutrition they got it late
उनको मिला क्या न्यूट्रिशन उनको मिला देर
Life Paths Diverge Widely
लाइफ देर लाइफ पाथ में डायवर्ज वाइडली
But they will have your DNA only, hmm
लेकिन डीएनए आपका ही होगा उनके पास हम्म
Ok ok moving on in 2065 it was also written
ओके ओके मूविंग ऑन 2065 में ये भी लिखा
Mars Colonization Phase One Kicks Off
गया है मार्स कॉलोनाइजेशन फेज वन किक्स ऑफ
I would like to say one thing, Mr.
मैं एक चीज कहना चाहूंगा बोले श्री
Ramakrishnan
रामकृष्णन
Joe actually I think is Donald Trump
जो एक्चुअली मेरे ख्याल से डोनल्ड ट्रंप
working with. Works out now
के साथ काम कर रहे हैं। अब ही वर्क्स आउट
Of the White House. I met him
ऑफ़ द वाइट हाउस। हम मैं उनसे मिला था
Almost 6 months ago. Good. From them I
ऑलमोस्ट 6 महीने पहले। अच्छा। उनसे मैंने
Asked about Elon Musk
ईलॉन मस्क के बारे में पूछा कि ईलॉन मस्क
What is the final goal? They said that
का फाइनल गोल क्या है? उन्होंने कहा कि
dude he is very very serious about mars
यार ही इज़ वेरी वेरीरी सीरियस अबाउट मार्स
Colonization. and every decision of he is
कॉलोनाइजेशन। एंड एव्री डिसजन ऑफ़ ह इज़
Based on colonizing Mars eventually. We
बेस्ड ऑन कॉलोनाइजिंग मार्स इवेंचुअली। हम
And here is the output of GPT saying that
और यहां जीपीटी का आउटपुट यह कह रहा है कि
Mars Colonization Phase One Kicks Off by 2065
2065 तक मार्स कॉलोनाइजेशन फेज वन किक ऑफ
hmm i myself will be 70 years old
हम्म मैं खुद 70 साल का होऊंगा 70 इयर्स
I Disagree With This Timeline Very Very Very
आई डिसएग्री विथ दिस टाइमलाइन वैरी वैरी
strongly think it's early i think it
स्ट्रोंगली थिंक इट्स अर्ली आई थिंक इट
will the first phase will be 20 30-31 wow ya
विल द फर्स्ट फेज विल बी 20 30-31 वाह या
but do you you you you you you think it
बट डू यू यू यू यू यू यू यू थिंक इट्स
Trying to do what they call terraforming
ट्राइंग टू से वो क्या कहते है टेराफोमिंग
Terraforming takes a thousand years
टेराफोमिंग तो हजार वर्ष लगते हैं उसको
Terraforming Is Not Something You Do in 20
टेराफॉर्मिंग इज नॉट समथिंग यू डू इन 20
What is terraforming?
ईयर क्या होती है टेराफोमिंग टेराफोमिंग
This means that you are on a new planet
का मतलब ये है कि आप आप एक नए प्लनेट पे
You go there and the environment there
जाते हो और वहां का जो एनवायरनमेंट है
You convert it through industrial scale
उसको आप बदलते हो थ्रू इंडस्ट्रियल स्केल
Pluri scale processes and your focus is this
प्लरी स्केल प्रोसेससेस और आपका धय ये है
Your goal is to protect the planet which
आपका लक्ष्य ये है कि उस प्लनेट का जो
Atmosphere is our environment
एटमॉस्फेयर है एनवायरनमेंट है वो हमारे
I think Elon made it like a planet
प्लनेट जैसा बना दे मेरे ख्याल से ईलॉन ने
he said on Joe Rogan that if terraformed
ही जो रोगन पर कहा था कि अगर टेराफॉर्म
The first step is to do that
करना है उसका पहला स्टेप होता है कि
heat up the planet because mars is very hot
प्लनेट को गर्म कर दो क्योंकि मार्स काफी
It is cold in comparison to our planet
ठंडा है हमारे प्लनेट के कंपैरिजन में तो
The first thing to do is to warm it up
पहला काम यह है कि उसको गर्म करो उसको
Its average temperature is about 25°
उसका जो एवरेज जो टेंपरेचर है वो लगभग 25°
Make it. Like average over meaning
बना दीजिए। जैसे अर्थ के ऊपर एवरेज
The temperature is 25°. So the first step is to
टेंपरेचर इज़ 25°। तो फर्स्ट स्टेप इज़ टू
do that on mars and then you can do another
डू दैट ऑन मार्स एंड देन यू कैन डू अदर
processes to thicken the atmosphere and have
प्रोसेससेस टू थिक द एटमॉस्फेयर एंड हैव
Liquid water and so on. But this process
लिक्विड वाटर एंड सो ऑन। लेकिन ये प्रोसेस
It is quite a long process. it will take two 300
काफी लंबा प्रोसेस है। इट विल टेक टू 300
Years perhaps. Minimum, minimum. Depends
इयर्स परहेप्स। मिनिमम, मिनिमम। डिपेंड्स
On which planet are you talking about? This
ऑन व्हिच प्लनेट यू आर टॉकिंग अबाउट? इसे
Just ask? Ask. Because I don't have many
ही पूछें? पूछिए। बिकॉज़ मैं ना बहुत सारे
I ask questions about cricket and football
क्रिकेट और फुटबॉल के सवाल पूछता हूं
From JBT. and i have notice that it gives
जेबीटी से। एंड आई हैव नोटिस दैट इट गिव्स
Me some rubbish output. Let's see what
मी सम रब्बीश आउटपुट। चलिए देखते हैं क्या
I say it. To be very honest. ok a
बोलते हैं। टू बी वैरी ऑनेस्ट। ओके अ
GBT which you have given the output of 2065
जीबीटी जो आपने 2065 का आउटपुट दिया है
mars colonization fuzz one kicks off a him
मार्स कॉलोनाइजेशन फज़ वन किक्स ऑफ अ उसे
Chavda sir is angry about this. They said that
लेकर चावड़ा सर नाराज हैं। उन्होंने कहा कि
he does not agree and he is saying that very
ही डजंट एग्री और वो कह रहे हैं कि वेरी
Likely this colonization much before that
लाइकली उससे बहुत पहले यह कॉलोनाइजेशन
It will be. So analyze yourself once.
होगी। तो खुद को एक बार एनालाइज कीजिए।
Ask yourself this question GPT you have solved this 2065
खुद से सवाल पूछिए जीपीटी आपने 2065 का यह
Why did you give points? and why not earlier
पॉइंट क्यों दिया? एंड व्हाई नॉट अर्लियर
Please answer in Hindi and whatever voice you use
प्लीज हिंदी में जवाब दीजिए और जो भी वॉइस
You are turning off the output, I am a bit scared
ऑफ आउटपुट कर रहे हो मुझे थोड़ा सा डर
It should be felt in your voice. Ok.
महसूस होना चाहिए आपके वॉइस में। ठीक है।
The estimate I gave for 2065 is different from many others.
मैंने 2065 का जो अनुमान दिया वो कई
considering the current challenges. As
मौजूदा चुनौतियों को देखते हुए था। जैसे
Technical limitations, funding and space
तकनीकी सीमाएं, फंडिंग और अंतरिक्ष में
The complexities of establishing human settlements. But
इंसानी बस्तियां बसाने की जटिलताएं। लेकिन
If progress is rapid and these challenges are met
अगर प्रगति तेजी से हो और इन चुनौतियों का
Mars colonization if the solution is found soon
समाधान जल्द मिल जाए तो मार्स कॉलोनाइजेशन
It might start even before that. It is possible
उससे पहले भी शुरू हो सकती है। हो सकता है
I guess be a little cautious.
मेरा अनुमान थोड़ा कॉशियस हो।
Do you want to ask him something? No I am my
कुछ पूछना है आपको इससे? नहीं मैं अपना
I can give the ration. I will explain my
रैशन दे सकता हूं। आई विल एक्सप्लेन माय
Rational why I said 2030 2031 see this
रैशनल व्हाई आई सेड 2030 2031 देखिए इस
Time if you want to go to Mars. near you
समय आपको अगर मार्स जाना है। आपके पास
You must have a very powerful rocket
आपके पास एक बहुत पावरफुल रॉकेट होना
Needed Elon Musk has just launched SpaceX
चाहिए। अभी ईलॉन मस्क ने स्पेस एक्स के
Built a rocket called Through Starship
थ्रू स्टारशिप नाम का एक रॉकेट बना लिया
Which is in the final stages of testing.
है जो फाइनल स्टेजेस ऑफ टेस्टिंग में है।
There are still some issues in it. but they have
अभी भी उसमें कुछ इश्यूज है। लेकिन दे हैव
The Money. they are the resources to do multiple
द मनी। दे आर द रिसोर्सेज टू डू मल्टीपल
Test a year by 2026 27 that rocket exactly
टेस्ट अ ईयर बाय 2026 27 वो रॉकेट बिल्कुल
It will be ready. Now every 26 months our
रेडी हो जाएगा। अभी हर 26 महीने में हमारे
There is a launch window to Mars because
पास लॉन्च विंडो होता है टू मार्स बिकॉज़
Of the plateau alignment. So Elon Musk's
ऑफ़ द प्लेटरी अलाइनमेंट। तो ईलॉन मस्क का
The objective is that initially an unmanned
ऑब्जेक्टिव है कि इनिशियली एक अनमैंड
SpaceShipIp will go there. a bunch of starships
स्पेसशिपिप वहां जाएगा। स्टारशिप अ बंच ऑफ
Unmanned launches will be done which are there
अनमैंड लॉन्चेस विल बी डन जो वहां पर
Will place cargo on the surface of Mars
कार्गो को प्लेस करेंगे मार्स के सरफेस के
to humans on top and in the next phase
ऊपर और नेक्स्ट फेज में ह्यूमंस को
Will send it possibly. So this is the first phase of
पॉसिबली भेजेंगे। तो ये फर्स्ट फेज ऑफ़
Unmanned launches to Mars will soon begin
अनमैंड लॉन्चेस टू मार्स अह विल बिगिन बाई
2030 2031. So this is their objective end
2030 2031. तो यह उनका ऑब्जेक्टिव है एंड
They are definitely on track to do that. So
दे आर डेफिनेटली ऑन ट्रैक टू डू दैट। तो
I disagree with this. if eilon
इसके लिए मैं डिसएग्री करता हूं। इफ ईलॉन
Musk is right if his company is on track
मस्क इज राइट इफ हिज कंपनी इज ऑन ट्रैक दे
will be able to do it by 2030 2031 that
विल बी एबल टू डू इट बाय 2030 2031 उस
a human around the time period
टाइम पीरियड के आसपास एक ह्यूमन
From perspective you can explain that life
पर्सपेक्टिव से आप समझा सकते हो कि लाइफ
on mars
ऑन मार्स
How will it look if we are inside a dome
हाउ विल इट लुक हम क्या हम एक डोम के अंदर
will it remain or will it appear as it is
रहेंगे या क्या वो अर्थ जैसे ही दिखेगी वो
Zindagi is a very good question initially
जिंदगी वेरी गुड क्वेश्चन इनिशियली हमें
Closed within Domed Environments
डोम्ड एनवायरनमेंट्स के अंदर क्लोज्ड
environments if
एनवायरनमेंट्स के अंदर रहना पड़ेगा अगर
We have to go out in the wide open marsh
हमें बाहर जाना है इनू द ओपन ओपन मार्श
We need to go into the atmosphere wearing a space suit
एटमॉस्फियर हमें स्पेस सूट पहन कर जाना
Our temperature will reach a livable level
पड़ेगा जो हमारा टेंपरेचर एक लिवबल लेवल
and it will keep water and oxygen till
तक रहेगा रखेगा और पानी और ऑक्सीजन वो
will supply but we will protect our skin
सप्लाई करेगा लेकिन हम अपनी स्किन को
will not be able to expose to the
एक्सपोज नहीं कर पा कर पाएंगे टू द
martian atmosphere because there is almost
मार्शियन एमॉस्फेयर बिकॉज़ वहां पे लगभग
The temperature is probably around -30
-30 के आसपास शायद टेंपरेचर होता है ऑन
Average on average so initially inside the domes
एवरेज ऑन एवरेज तो इनिशियली डोम्स के अंदर
and within close environments
और क्लोज क्लोज एनवायरनमेंट्स के अंदर
You will eventually have to live for 100-200 years
रहना पड़ेगा इवेंचुअली 100 200 साल के
If we increased the temperature inside
अंदर अगर हमने उसका टेंपरेचर बढ़ा दिया
From Mars we may be able to go outside
मार्स का देन वी मे बी एबल टू गो आउटसाइड
with mask gas mask and what oxygen
विथ मास्क गैस मास्क और व्हाट ऑक्सीजन
Mask and walk around so it's slow
मास्क एंड वॉक अराउंड तो यह धीरे-धीरे
I am wondering if there will be changes in this
चेंजेस आएंगे इसमें मैं सोच रहा हूं अगर
Some crazy person staying inside that dome throws a stone
कोई पागल उस डोम के अंदर रहकर एक पत्थर
If he throws me on the dome then the rest will be humans
फेंकेगा डोम पे हम तो फिर बाकी इंसान होगा
what will happen look yes this is obviously
क्या होगा देखिए हां ये ये ऑब्वियसली हमें
We have to consider this when we design the DOM
कंसीडर करना पड़ेगा जब हम डोम को डिजाइन
Let's bring someone's mental balance in check
करते हैं लेट्स से किसी का मानसिक संतुलन
got spoiled and he tried to break it
खराब हो गया और उसने तोड़ने की कोशिश की
If you try to break it then first of all you
तोड़ने का प्रयत्न किया तो आपको सबसे पहले
We will have to see the thickness of the dome
डोम का थिकनेस देखना देखना पड़ेगा कितना
How thick do you want to make it? How much
थिकनेस कितना थिक आपको बनाना है। कितना
You have to make yourself resilient
रेिलिएंट बनाना है आपको कि आपको
I need unbreakable glass. If you have multiple
अनब्रेकेबल ग्लास चाहिए। अगर आपको मल्टीपल
You have to give layers to the dome, think about that too
लेयर्स देने हैं डोम के वो भी सोचना
It will have to be done. Then you also have to think about
पड़ेगा। फिर आपको यह भी सोचना पड़ेगा किसी
shot for example and all of them
ने शूट किया फॉर एग्जांपल और सारे के सारे
If the layer gets punctured then you should immediately
लेयर पंक्चर हो गए तो उसका आपको इमीडिएट
What remedial major need to be done and so on.
रिमीडियल मेजर क्या करना होगा एंड सो ऑन।
So we will design after thinking about all this. and I
तो ये सब सोच कर ही डिजाइन करेंगे। एंड आई
I'm sure they make a good job of that.
एम श्योर दे मेक डू अ गुड जॉब ऑफ़ दैट।
Salute to the mind and passion of Elon Musk. That
ईलॉन मस्क के दिमाग और जज्बे को सलाम। कि
This is a very gutsy move. Absolutely. Absolutely
बहुत गटसी मूव है ये। बिल्कुल। बिल्कुल
Definitely. How do you even think that friend
डेफिनेटली। सोचते भी कैसे हैं कि यार
I want to go and live in Mars. hum what do you
मार्स में जाकर रहना है। हम् व्हाट डू यू
Think why is he thinking this way? now only
थिंक व्हाई इज ही थिंकिंग दिस वे? नाउ ही
Is definitely a pioneer. Definitely
इज़ अ डेफिनेटली अ पायोनियर। डेफिनेटली
The Pioneer. He has always thought this way. Ahhh
पायोनियर। ही हैज़ ऑलवेज थॉट दिस वे। अह
many people think about these things but he is
मेनी पीपल थिंक अबाउट दीज़ थिंग्स बट ही इज़
actually done ah took the steps in the actions
एक्चुअली डन अह टेकन द स्टेप्स इन द एकशंस
that are potentially going to allow him to do
दैट आर पोटेंशियली गोइंग अलाउ हिम टू डू
actually be the first person to have a
एक्चुअली बी द फर्स्ट पर्सन टू हैव अ
Rocket going to mass. not a government but a
रॉकेट गोइंग टू मास। नॉट अ गवर्नमेंट बट अ
Private company. Imagine that. Ok. Or
प्राइवेट कंपनी। इमेजिन दैट। ओके। या
We have arrived in 2070
हम पहुंचे हैं 2070
till
तक
Cancer cured by nanobots
कैंसर क्यर्ड बाय नैनोबॉट्स नैनोबॉट्स के
I read about it in school in 2006 or so
बारे में मैंने पढ़ा था स्कूल में 2006 या
we have been talking since seven that's it
सात में हम तब से बात हो रही है दैट्स
almost 20 years ago now we but I don't
ऑलमोस्ट 20 इयर्स एगो नाउ हम बट आई डोंट
Some technology advances in No Nanobots
नो नैनोबॉट्स में कुछ टेक्नोलॉजी एडवांस
whether it has happened or not then we can
हुई भी है कि नहीं हो रही होंगी तो वी कैन
Decide We Can First Discuss Nanobots
डिसाइड वी कैन फर्स्ट डिसकस नैनोबॉट होते
what is it yes there are small machines
क्या है हां छोटे से मशीनंस होते हैं
How many small, how many small, I mean almost
कितने छोटे कितने छोटे छोटे मतलब ऑलमोस्ट
They operate at an invisible microscopic level
इनविज़िबल माइक्रोस्कोपिक लेवल पर वो ऑपरेट
We do. inside your body inside your body
करते हैं। आपके बॉडी के आपके शरीर के अंदर
Can get into your bloodstream.
आपके ब्लड स्ट्रीम के अंदर जा सकते हैं।
Can repair separate individual cells
अलग इंडिविजुअल सेल्स को रिपेयर कर सकते
Are. By going into individual sales,
हैं। इंडिविजुअल सेल्स के अंदर जाकर उनके
Components can also be modified.
कंपोनेंट्स को भी मॉडिफाई कर सकते हैं।
mitochondria or whatever else
माइटोकांड्रिया या फिर व्हाटएवर और
It is saying that these nanobots will go to your
यह कह रहा है कि ये नैनोबॉट्स जाएंगे आपके
inside the body and they will know which cell
बॉडी के अंदर और वो जानेंगे कि कौन सा सेल
which cells are healthy, which cells are cancerous and those
हेल्दी है, कौन सा सेल कैंसरस है और उन
They will be able to destroy the cancerous cells. So
कैंसरस सेल्स को वो नष्ट कर पाएंगे। तो
This will be a targeted therapy. You get an injection
टारगेटेड थेरेपी होगी ये। आप एक इंजेक्शन
Give it. 1 lakh from let's in that injection
दीजिए। उस इंजेक्शन में लेट्स से 1 लाख
There are nanobots. Hypothetically give such numbers
नैनोबॉट्स हैं। हाइपोथेटिकली ऐसे नंबर दे
I have been. these nanobots will go and
रहा हूं। ये नैनोबॉट्स जाएंगे और एक
within a week, as many cells inside your body as
सप्ताह के अंदर आपके शरीर के अंदर जितने
Whatever cancer cells there are, they will destroy them all.
भी कैंसर सेल होंगे सबको नष्ट कर देंगे।
So this is a cure for cancer. So say this
तो दिस इज अ क्योर फॉर कैंसर। तो ये बोल
This is what they are saying. Little
रही है ये दैट्स व्हाट दे आर सेइंग। थोड़ा
Check the same question in 20 years
चेक कर ले वही सवाल कि 20 साल में
What has been the progress? Hi GBT we are
प्रोग्रेस क्या हुआ है? हाय जीबीटी हम
have reached 2070. where you wrote that
2070 तक पहुंचे हैं। जहां आपने लिखा है कि
Cancer cured by nanobots. But this whole
कैंसर क्यर्ड बाय नैनोबॉट्स। पर इस पूरे
For the first time you can see Nano Bobots in the table
टेबल में पहली बार आप नैनो बबॉट्स को
You are mentioning directly 2070.
मेंशन कर रहे हो डायरेक्टली 2070 में।
That means nanobots had no role before that
यानी कि उससे पहले नैनोबॉट्स का कोई रोल
Will it not remain in human life? These
रहेगा ही नहीं क्या ह्यूमन लाइफ में? ये
Tell me. Tell me five things about a nanobot
बताइए। पांच चीजें बताइए अ नैनोबॉट से
Related. Ok? Nanobes Tiny Machines One
रिलेटेड। ठीक है? नैनोब्स टाइनी मशीनंस वन
to 100 nanometers in size can be
टू 100 नैनोमीटर्स इन साइज कैन बी
programmed to perform specific tasks
प्रोग्राम्ड टू परफॉर्म स्पेसिफिक टास्क
On a microscopic level. Hum Bye 2030
ऑन अ माइक्रोस्कोपिक लेवल। हम बाय 2030
Early Clinical Use Targeted Drug
अर्ली क्लीनिकल यूज़ टारगेटेड ड्रग
Delivery. Nanopots Can Carry Chemotherapy
डिलीवरी। नैनोपॉट्स कैन कैरी केमोथेरेपी
Only two cancer cells. That means when you
ओनली टू कैंसर सेल्स। यानी कि जब आप
Do you undergo chemotherapy treatment?
केमोथेरेपी की ट्रीटमेंट करते हो, आपकी
There are side effects on the entire body.
पूरी बॉडी पर साइड इफेक्ट्स होते हैं।
Absolutely they do. So they are saying that
बिल्कुल होते हैं। तो ये कह रहे हैं कि
Nanobots can give you targeted recovery. We
नैनोबॉट्स कैन गिव यू टारगेटेड रिकवरी। हम
A blood stream surveillance nanobots your
अ ब्लड स्ट्रीम सर्वेलेंस नैनोबॉट्स आपके
Basically all blood levels will be scanned.
बेसिकली ब्लड लेवल सब स्कैन करेंगे।
Inflammation level what can't they check at all
इनफ्लेमेशन लेवल व्हाट नॉट दे कैन चेक ऑल
It. and when some small problem occurs
इट। और जब कुछ ऐसे छोटी-मोटी गड़बड़ हो
Nanobes will go into your body and tell you
जाएगी आपकी बॉडी में नैनोब्स बताएंगे
To you. But these are all early clinical uses.
आपको। पर ये सब अर्ली क्लीनिकल यूज़ है।
Micro Surgeries Non Invasive Procedures
माइक्रो सर्जरीज नॉन इन्वेसिव प्रोसीजर्स
From inside your body. Wow. think of a
फ्रॉम इनसाइड योर बॉडी। वाह। थिंक ऑफ अ
Nanobots Clearing Artery Blockages
नैनोबॉट क्लियरिंग आर्टरी ब्लॉकेज
Interesting Cost Estimate
इंटरेस्टिंग कॉस्ट एस्टीमेट
10 to 30 Lacs per session initially Hum Mass
10 टू 30 लैक्स पर सेशन इनिशियली हम मास
used by 20-40 could bring it below one to
यूज्ड बाय 20-40 कुड ब्रिंग इट बिलो वन टू
2 lax ok good bye 20 40 to 50 anti
2 लैक्स ओके गुड बाय 20 40 टू 50 एंटी
Aging Therapies Brain Machine Interface Increases
एजिंग थेरेपीस ब्रेन मशीन इंटरफेस इंक्रीस
In Immunity Immunity 2.0 we end
इन इम्यूनिटी इम्यूनिटी 2.0 हम एंड
Anobots Update Your Immunity Systems
एनोबॉट्स अपडेट योर इम्यूनिटी सिस्टम्स
like a software patch nice
लाइक अ सॉफ्टवेयर पैच नाइस
Ah a basically given a scenario that if
अह अ बेसिकली एक सिनेरियो दिया है कि अगर
You are unwell, you are wearing a wearable patch
आपकी तबीयत खराब है आप एक वेरेबल पैच पहन
Take. Then that patch will have nanobots in it.
लो। फिर उस पैच में नैनोबॉट्स होंगे।
The nanobots will go into your bloodstream.
नैनोबॉट्स जाएंगे आपके ब्लड स्ट्रीम में।
Your body will also be scanned. If
आपकी बॉडी को स्कैन भी कर देंगे। अगर
There is a bacterial infection, bacteria also
बैक्टीरियल इंफेक्शन है, बैक्टीरिया को भी
I will destroy it. Antibiotics too
डिस्ट्रॉय कर देंगे। एंटीबायोटिक्स भी
Will release it and all this within 10 minutes
रिलीज कर देंगे और यह सब 10 मिनट के अंदर
You won't even know if you were sick or
आपको पता भी नहीं चलेगा कि आप बीमार थे या
No. We are good. what would you like to say to
नहीं। हम गुड। क्या कहना चाहोगे आप टू
Conclude this nanobots angle? See
कंक्लूड दिस नैनोबॉट्स एंगल? देखिए
Nanobes is a very interesting technology.
नैनोब्स बहुत इंटरेस्टिंग टेक्नोलॉजी है।
They are like small construction machinery
दे आर लाइक स्मॉल कंस्ट्रक्शन मशीनरी
Strommo Small Machine Tiny Microscopic
स्ट्रोमो स्माल मशीन टाइनी माइक्रोस्कोपिक
Robots, they have a lot of potential. a their
रोबोट्स उनका पोटेंशियल बहुत है। अ उनका
now as we saw they are still in the
अभी जैसे हमने देखा दे आर स्टिल इन द
experimental fuzz but if that cancer
एक्सपेरिमेंटल फज़ लेकिन अगर वो कैंसर
can detect cells and
सेल्स को डिटेक्ट कर सकते हैं और उनको
You can target. that will definitely
टारगेट कर सकते हैं। दैट विल डेफिनेटली
Cure Cancer Any Type of Liver Cancer
क्योर कैंसर किसी भी प्रकार का कैंसर लिवर
Cancer, kidney cancer, brain cancer,
कैंसर, किडनी कैंसर, ब्रेन कैंसर,
Whatever else, cancer. even blood cancer, bone
व्हाटएवर एल्स कैंसर। इवन ब्लड कैंसर, बोन
Marrow cancer. So if that one thing happens
मैरो कैंसर। सो वो एक ही अगर एक चीज हो गई
that will be a revolution in health care to
दैट विल बी अ रेवोल्यूशन इन हेल्थ केयर तो
Nanobots have many different uses in drugs
नैनोबॉट्स के बहुत अलग-अलग यूज है ड्रग
Delivery is not what I think is the biggest
डिलीवरी व्हाट नॉट आई थिंक सबसे बड़ा
The challenge with nanobots is that they
चैलेंज नैनोबॉट्स को लेकर ये है कि वो
You are so small that you give me plus
होते ही इतने छोटे हैं तो प्लस दे आर
machines give machines to make these machines
मशीनंस दे मशीनंस पर इन मशीनंस को बनाने
Small machines would be needed for this also
के लिए भी छोटे मशीनंस लगते होंगे
Probably the manufacturing is the big one
प्रोब्ली द मैन्युफैक्चरिंग इज द बिग
The functioning is the challenge which machines
चैलेंज द फंक्शनिंग इज द चैलेंज जो मशीनंस
This is the manufacturing scale of Nanoba
ये जो नैनोबा का मैन्युफैक्चरिंग स्केल है
it is similar to the scale at which you
इट इज सिमिलर टू द स्केल एट व्हिच यू
Create Microchips.
क्रिएट माइक्रोचिप्स।
Your GPUs, CPUs etc.
आपके जो जीपीयूस है, सीपीयूज़ एटसेट्रा वो
also on the same type of scale we
भी उसी उसी प्रकार के स्केल के ऊपर हम
Let's create it. so i think the technology
क्रिएट करते हैं। सो आई थिंक द टेक्नोलॉजी
there must be some similarity to create the
में कुछ तो सिमिलरिटी होगी टू क्रिएट द
Nano bots. we are okay guys this podcast
ननो बॉट्स। हम ओके अ दोस्तों इस पॉडकास्ट
At the beginning of 2015 we thought we would be 22
के शुरुआत में हमने सोचा था कि हम 22
We will draw out a timeline till then. Ah But Age
तक एक टाइमलाइन ड्रॉ आउट करेंगे। अह बट एज
We've gone forward in this podcast.
वी हैव गॉन फॉरवर्ड इन दिस पॉडकास्ट।
This is an experimental episode for us too.
हमारे लिए भी एक एक्सपेरिमेंटल एपिसोड है।
A we have decided to cap it out at the 50s
अ वी हैव डिसाइडेड टू कैप इट आउट एट द 50
Ear mark. Makes sense. because we look at
ईयर मार्क। मेक सेंस। क्योंकि हमें देखना
that what is your response. You
है कि आपकी रिस्पांस क्या है। यू
Interested in conversations like this. Plus
इंटरेस्टेड इन कन्वर्सेशंस लाइक दिस। प्लस
If you actually forward this same document
अगर आप एक्चुअली इस सेम डॉक्यूमेंट को आगे
Scan on the same timeline then it becomes
स्कैन करें उसी टाइमलाइन पे तो इट बिकम्स
More and more speculative. AI Edge in Chat
मोर एंड मोर स्पेकुलेटिव। एआई एज इन चैट
Even GBD itself doesn't exactly know that
जीबीडी को भी खुद एक्सैक्टली नहीं पता कि
What will happen in the future? These are all guesses.
फ्यूचर में क्या होगा। ये सब तुक्के हैं।
which is why i think its a good point
व्हिच इज व्हाई आई थिंक इट्स अ गुड पॉइंट
to and a first experimental episode on
टू एंड अ फर्स्ट एक्सपेरिमेंटल एपिसोड ऑन
Futurism so definitely 50 years makes sense.
फ्यूचरिज्म सो डेफिनेटली 50 ईयर मेक सेंस।
yes may be in the last bit this is from the table
हां मे बी इन द लास्ट बिट यही टेबल से इज
there's anything that catches your eye
देयर एनीथिंग दैट्स कॉट योर आई जो आपको
I felt that yes friend this may be we should have
लगा कि हां यार ये मे बी वी शुड हैव
Discussed it. you can just scan it like
डिस्कस्ड इट। यू कैन जस्ट स्कैन इट लाइक
Quickly. I think we have covered most of the
क्विकली। आई थिंक वी हैव कवर्ड मोस्ट ऑफ़ द
Interesting stuff. I would like to say that
इंटरेस्टिंग स्टफ। मैं यह कहना चाहूंगा कि
AI is developing very fast right now. We
एआई इज़ डेवलपिंग वैरी फास्ट राइट नाउ। हम
It has already reached this level that we
ऑलरेडी इस इस लेवल पर पहुंच गए हैं कि वी
We Almost Have Artificial General Intelligence
ऑलमोस्ट हैव आर्टिफिशियल जनरल इंटेलिजेंस
which is an ai system whose intelligence
व्हिच इज एन एआई सिस्टम जिसका इंटेलिजेंस
The level is equal to a person with 130 IQ
लेवल इज इक्वल टू अ पर्सन विद 130 आईक्यू
hmm we are already at that level but almost
हम्म हम ऑलरेडी उस स्तर पर पर ऑलमोस्ट
We have arrived. I may be back in two-three years
पहुंच चुके हैं। मे बी दो-ती साल में हो
Will go. I have done it privately but
जाएगा। मे बी प्राइवेटली हो चुका है लेकिन
It has not been announced to the public. Now if
पब्लिक में अनाउंस नहीं हुआ है। अब अगर
You have an AGI system, artificially
आपके पास एजीआई सिस्टम है आर्टिफिशियली
If you have a general intelligence system then that
जनरल इंटेलिजेंस सिस्टम है आपके पास तो वो
can improve itself. it can improve
अपने आप को सुधार सकता है। इट कैन इंप्रूव
Itself and very soon you will have an AI
इटसेल्फ एंड वेरी सून यू विल हैव एन एआई
After that whose IQ level is human
उसके बाद जिसका आईक्यू लेवल है ह्यूमन
The equivalent of being 300 and there is no
बीइंग के इक्विवेलेंट 300 एंड देयर इज़ नो
Human with IQ 300 it is a super
ह्यूमन विथ आईक्यू 300 इट इज़ अ सुपर
What is called Intelligent AI
इंटेलिजेंट एआई जिसको बोलते हैं
Artificial Super Intelligence. this is me b 5
आर्टिफिशियल सुपर इंटेलिजेंस। ये मे बी 5
It will happen within a year. if you have
साल में हो जाएगा। अगर आपके पास
If there is artificially super intelligent AI then
आर्टिफिशियली सुपर इंटेलिजेंट एआई है तो
He will create such technology for you that
वह ऐसी टेक्नोलॉजी बनाएगा आपके लिए जो
You will feel magic. Time Travel Think Worm
आपको मैजिक लगेगी। टाइम ट्रैवल सोचिए वर्म
holes traversable worm holes all of that
होल्स ट्रेवर्सबल वर्म होल्स ये सब कुछ
Not what we saw. once you have asi
नहीं है जो हमने देखा। वंस यू हैव एएसआई
Artificial Super Intelligence. then magic
आर्टिफिशियल सुपर इंटेलिजेंस। देन मैजिक
will be accessible to you. we i say so
विल बी एक्सेबल टू यू। हम मैं तो कहता हूं
The government which will implement this technology in 5-10 years
5 10 साल में जो गवर्नमेंट इस टेक्नोलॉजी
will crack it. he to the whole world
को क्रैक कर लेगी। वो पूरे विश्व को
Will rule for the next thousand years. we this
नेक्स्ट हजार वर्ष तक रूल करेगी। हम यह
This is the situation.
सिचुएशन है।
It was a very experimental podcast
बहुत ही ज्यादा एक्सपेरिमेंटल पॉडकास्ट था
it. But I had fun with you. i think it's a
यह। बट मजा आया आपके साथ। आई थिंक इट्स अ
New Dimension on the Show. Thank you sir. Kud
न्यू डायमेंशन ऑन द शो। थैंक यू सर। कुड
I couldn't have done it with anyone else. but this is
नॉट हैव डन इट विथ एनीवन एल्स। बट दिस इज
A Deeply Experimental Episode. i hope you
अ डीपली एक्सपेरिमेंटल एपिसोड। आई होप यू
Head Fun as Well. Absolutely. Honestly,
हेड फन एज वेल। अब्सोल्युटली। ऑनेस्टली,
I think GPT has crashed on my phone
आई थिंक जीपीटी मेरे फोन पे क्रैश हो चुका
Is. Which is why I also consider GPT as good
है। व्हिच इज व्हाई मैं जीपीटी को भी गुड
Unable to say bye. but i hope the audience
बाय नहीं कह पा रहा। बट आई होप दी ऑडियंस
Enjoyed it. and we'll be back with another
एन्जॉयड इट। एंड वी विल बी बैक विथ अनदर
Great science episode very-very soon. thank you
ग्रेट साइंस एपिसोड वैरी-वेरी सून। थैंक
You. Thank you. So friends, this was today's
यू। थैंक यू। तो दोस्तों, यह था आज का
Experimental Blockbuster Episode. Tell me
एक्सपेरिमेंटल ब्लॉकबस्टर एपिसोड। बताइए
How did you like the episode? ofcourse like me
एपिसोड कैसा लगा? ऑफकोर्स, जैसे कि मैं
I keep saying AC Sir will come back to TRS
कहते रहता हूं एसी सर लौट कर आएंगे टीआरएस
But. So keep supporting us. keep sending end
पर। तो कीप सपोर्टिंग अस। कीप सेंडिंग एंड
Recommendations for these episodes. Such tech and
रेकमेंडेशंस फॉर दीज़ एपिसोड्स। ऐसे टेक और
The science episodes are very dear to my heart
साइंस वाले एपिसोड्स मेरे दिल के बहुत
It's close. but i am looking for guest
करीब है। बट आई एम लुकिंग फॉर गेस्ट
Recommendations as well as topic recommendations.
रेकमेंडेशंस एस वेल एस टॉपिक रेकमेंडेशंस।
So, send in your input and we will follow up
सो, सेंड इन योर इनपुट एंड वी विल फॉलो अप
On TRS. The Run Show will return with this Sir
ऑन टीआरएस। इसी सर लौट कर आएंगे द रन शो
But. but until then keep supporting, keep
पर। बट अंटिल देन कीप सपोर्टिंग, कीप
Listening, keep growing.
लिसनिंग, कीप ग्रोइंग।
[music]
[संगीत]